I don't know what those letters meant in blue.
I'm obsessed.
I am obsessed.
I am obsessed
Yeah, I think we will
I think we'll at least explain
My goal is to explain like
mental model, way to think about it
and maybe build a little something
along the way. No promises it'll look good
but it should be at least functional
But yeah
So I also
like before we started just wanted to like
sort of catch up and see how you've been
doing with all this like
working with React for the past
few years. It feels like React Server Components
has been going
for a long time or I've heard about it
for a long time and it's taken many forms
and I'm kind of curious like what did
it take to get to this point
like what was the process
there and the collaboration
Yeah
So I think we first
started like specifically
Sebastian
is like the person who tends
to
kind of look at our vision
going forward like he started thinking
about this maybe in 2016
so
there he had a
internal document
called perhaps provocatively
what comes
after GraphQL
and the idea
was
basically the architecture
like the architecture we had
at Meta for
like
for web apps
was using GraphQL
and Relay for
data access and that worked pretty
well but what ends up
happening is you
you push more and more code
to the client
and so like the client bundle really
grows but that's
also not the whole story it's like
you also push a lot
data like the traditional kind
of rich client architecture
is you push all the data
that you might kind of plausibly
need into a client cache
and then your components pick parts
of the data and somehow massage it
and so what you
the problem you kind of run into
you know as you scale it up is
you end
up having all the data
and all the code you might possibly need
even if actually
it's not needed for the specific
case and
like a canonical
example of this could be
you know like when you want
to show you know a post was
liked by
like your friend
like I don't know
Dan and like Anna
and like five others
something like this and so you don't
actually need for example
their avatars
or
and like you need like very specific bits
of information and really like it's just
you don't even need like the links to their
profiles it's really
just the string that you want to get
but even though the GraphQL
of course like GraphQL lets you be very selective
about what you fetch
and like how you use it so it does
solve this problem partially
but you still
the shape of the data you
download is dictated by the GraphQL
endpoint and so if you
like transform a bunch of
stuff and
get you know like get something
that you know just the
data for the UI layer you kind of
have to do it on the client
and this problem
it's like an inefficiency problem
I think that's like one way
you know one way to think of this is like
we'd like to optimize it so
that like the natural way
to optimize it if you think about it is
okay like you're on the server anyway
why not have some kind of
abstraction kind of like view models
that used to be like a thing
in I don't know 20
2010 or something like this there was
this idea of like view models that
massage the actual model from the
database for the view kind of
preparing just what the view
needs
and I think that's one
angle and it doesn't
have to do like I also want to clarify
it doesn't have to do with like just like big
pages or anything like
a classic kind of low
scale example of this is a documentation
website where you
have like you have many
MDX components
like you know code
snippets or interactive code
editor and so on and
the way you would do this today
probably is you just have
like all of them in a single
bundle and then like all of them get
loaded but ideally what you want
is like if a page has no
interactive code snippets and also
only has like static code
examples you probably don't want to like
download the parser you kind of want to have
that output instead
so I think like that is like
one part of it is this idea
like let's not download the data
we're not going to need let's not
download the code we might
not need let's
just you know download
the things that we actually do need and then
if you need to like pre-process a bunch of stuff
we'll just do that on the server because
we're going to the server anyway
why not do it there
but I think another
way to look at it is just from the
mental model perspective
so if you've been coding
you know like for a while
like especially like before
like before all the client
stuff explosion
which you know it was warranted like people
wanted to do more stuff on the client
because they wanted to have like
zero latency
for like interactions and like really
reach interactions without reloading the page
but then if you think in terms of
like mental model
kind of thinking in terms of
like state management and
caching and like all of this stuff
it gets really complicated
like how do you even know like what to
fetch for the next page how do you
avoid waterfalls
like it gets pretty complex and then if you
think of like the way we used to write
web apps in you know
in 2000s before
like in traditional server
client model the mental model is
so much simpler because you just describe
like I'm going to go to the database
I'm going to fetch these different things I'm going to spit
out this response and then
if you want to like go to another page
that cycle repeats again
and so I think like server components
is you know kind of this idea of
let's keep the user
experience where like things
don't you know you don't reload the page
all the time but let's
keep also like the mental model
of the kind of traditional
request response
where you just
describe what you want to see on the page
and then it somehow reconciles
and also like
let's while we're here why
not like apply a bunch of optimizations
now that we know you know like let's not download
more code than we need let's not
download more data and so
in terms of like historical scale
I think we so we
started with this
I think like idea of
and we knew we also knew that
you know this approach was also
not new exactly it was more about
bringing it to react
because for
like we've had
at Facebook we've had XHP
so this is
Wait what is XHP?
It's sort of like an alternative universe
and I think we're kind of
seeing this again with
you know like when JSX was weird
to everyone when react came out
and we didn't even realize that it
would be controversial
I think like with server components maybe
it's a little bit similar because
the thing we had
before react
the way like the
Facebook website was built
was with like PHP and later
changed to hack
but we have this syntax for
defining
components there
so it was a very different
mindset from
I guess dominant solutions like
Rails or
you know like the old school
server solutions
like in the open source
XHP was pretty different because it felt
more like react as in
you have no like there are no
additional controllers in
this kind of MVC sense
it's more like there's a component
tree, components can be
asynchronous so they can like fetch
some data and then return what they render
and you can compose them
and you can have your own components
and so this is actually like
where JSX came from
is like people writing XHP
code wanted to keep writing
something similar like on the client
but the problem with that paradigm is that
it couldn't refresh
without like losing the entire page
and so
we had this thing as inspiration
and we also had
our native apps also kind of worked
like at least some
parts of them worked with that model where
the actual logic for how
to massage data and like turn it
into UI tree was on the server
it was written in XHP
Is that kind of like PHP?
I mean I see the similarity
conceptually of just like you're
wild-westing your database queries here
you're turning that into server markup
and then you're sending it down. It's just there was no
like server-client relationship yet
so I kind of see that React like took that
bit out, the templating was the good part
let's do the client thing first because that's
kind of a no-brainer of like yeah that's
like the end of the spectrum
that's what you need and now
we're kind of cycling back
when we realized oh yeah we probably could
have a dynamic setup here
yeah I think it's
it's just that we already
had a solution to the server part
and like XHP was actually
pretty sophisticated so
there was another part that was
related to it called BigPipe
which we you know like we published
an article about it in
2011 maybe
and it's just
this idea that if you have
this kind of like asynchronous
component abstraction on the server
you also don't want to
like hold the entire page
before starting to
like emit output
and I was actually
surprised like I learned that in
PHP or Rails like you would
usually just you know
fetch everything and kind of then
start rendering and like that's
not efficient
and so yeah
so the way like BigPipe worked is that
it had this ability to chunk
the page like your feed your
like I don't know like the sidebar
something else those could be
parallelized
so like all of them could have some data
dependencies but we could stream
kind of the initial shell and then fill
them in and so we wanted to bring
like so I think like we had
these solutions
but then we needed client
interactivity and so React
kind of started solving that
and then as we kind of did more
with React
there was like this split between
technologies that became very noticeable
because they did not really
integrate well
no they were used together
so you could in XHP
you could render a React component
but this would only
work kind of once so this
would just say you know like
in this like tree
when it loads on the client like put
this React component there but then there
was no way to update the tree because
it was just HTML in the end
so there was no
way to kind of refresh it without losing
the page
okay so there was no
like client side routing story
is kind of the big part there
yeah well it's not just
routing necessarily it's just there was no
way to refresh the server
output without like losing everything
and so
I think the
yeah so I think
the story kind of
it really became
I think like
the way to explain it
conceptually
makes more
sense like if you do this in a different
order then things actually happen
chronologically yeah it does make
sense because server components are like it's fitting
this thing that's actually a new starting
point instead of a new feature
so it's like if you want to use it
properly you
refactor from the top you're not refactoring
by just let's add a server component right here
and see how it goes exactly
yeah and I think it's because
like we've already like we've had a piece
you know that works on the server so we did
the client part and now okay let's
rethink the server piece
to work with the client part seamlessly
because we now know you know the entire
like how to fit them
together and so that
took a long time and I think like suspense
is especially interesting as a feature
because the original
the
motivation for his design which
I think was in like 2016 or
2017 yeah was
like how do we adopt this
big pipe architecture like
this idea of streaming things
in and like having them kind of appear
as they're ready like
how do we fit this into React
server rendering model
and so we started there that let
that let the like design of suspense
then but the first
way we shift suspense was actually on the client
only and it was not supported for
SSR because we didn't have a streaming
server render yet and then we did like
streaming server rendering and then
we realized actually this still leads
to waterfalls because like then
your app lives on the client
and you need to somehow prevent
client server waterfalls
and so then we're like okay maybe we need like
to actually like do something like
XFP first or you know like
do something that actually lets you avoid
client server waterfalls
and this idea of like splitting
components into two types
was actually using like
almost the same mechanism as
Sebastian explored in
2015 but for
using Reacting workers
so it's
exactly the same idea but applied
like a different so it's like many things
came together that were developed
in like in different years and
now like we have this consistent vision
but it's it's a bit hard
to unpack how it happened exactly
it yeah and it's
it's cool to hear the context of like
where this was born inside
of Facebook because it starts
to make a little more sense with that I just know it
as like an outsider that used
React first with create React app
then with Next.js and just kind of learn
patterns from there for small scale things
without ever really thinking about the server
it was like I learned about client stuff
then I learned about SSR and now
I'm pushing everything that I can to the server
it's backwards from how like
the progress of web
dev happened like it started with Rails
and then we started exploring client side
but I'm like in a generation
that started with Angular 1 like
I was middle school before
that so I just didn't even know what was
going on in web dev before that
so it's just different
yeah I guess the other
thing that's like relevant is I think a lot
of people because like the
word server is so like overloaded
in like for us at
least because we
we try to solve like a more
general problem so
like server components for example
they can run during the
build right so it doesn't
mean that you literally need to like have
a server it's more like
the server client distinction
for us is just
the stuff that runs first and kind of
the stuff that runs later and so
the stuff that runs first that could run
during the build time or
where actually
it won't do and it also gets confusing
right because like client components
they kind of also run on the server
during like SSR
so it's not
exactly this like client
stuff is like in the browser server
stuff is like on the machine
it's more like just two stages and we need
some names for the stages
and we also want to support
running server components
on the client
of course you wouldn't be able to
read a database but it's just
using the same mental model
if you really don't have a server and
also you don't want to
you know generate things
at the build time but you want to structure
your code like in the same way so that
it's later possible to like extend
it or like port it
so it's really about the paradigm
of like this you know
two component types
rather than specific places where you put
them
yeah exactly and I've heard
the thought in the past
of like maybe it should have been called use
interactive or something like that
where it implies like I'm not a fan of
that personally but it
implies that it's adding things
that could basically
change state after the fact
it's not just passing things down through server
components and it's like
I get it I think my bigger
maybe not issue but
when you hear React server components you think server
immediately that's definitely a thing
but it really just means
thing that doesn't run in the browser
necessarily usually
you would do like a static build up front
and then ship anything down that you can
or if you want to stream and suspense
stuff then you can go
boot up the server and
Next.js is pretty graceful with that where it's like
actually figuring out what could
be sandwiched into a big cache and what
can't so you don't really have to think about that
but if you're building it on your own
I totally agree that server components
are just like
pre-rendering I think is one word I've heard
also like build time versus
server it could be either one
so build time components it just
depends where you're running it
yeah
it's confusing I think it's
one of those cases where everybody has
suggestions on how to name them but then
they don't seem
they all have weird cases
where it's not exactly true
and server client is
like
maybe this is one of those
cases where we just
redefine the terms
like rendering
in React rendering
doesn't mean updating the
the graphical
like it's a different concept
from rendering in graphics
programming because like in React I
re-render it doesn't mean that
a bunch of stuff actually changes on the screen
it just means we recompute what should
be on the screen and like maybe we change something
maybe we don't and so people have
intuitions like oh I have to avoid re-rendering
but actually you don't it's
just a question of like is it actually slow
if it's not slow you're fine
like everything is fine and so
we kind of hijacked this definition
like in React rendering means
something different and I feel like maybe
this is another example of like yeah we kind of
we need some words to describe
the relationship and these are the best words
we found but it's gonna
be a bit confusing and we haven't
found any better options so far
yeah
it goes all down the stack and
I work at Astro right now
and you know maintaining a meta framework
we were dealing with these really primitive ideas
where it's like you don't want to use
complicated names for this stuff you want it
to feel accessible but
it also needs to describe what it does
pretty well I also know
with React like a big debacle came around
use as just like a term
that you can use to unwrap
something that happens later
and like I'm getting used
to it I suggested
unwrap and people are like well not always
sometimes use is used for this
use use that's also
a thing so it's hard
you want it to be simple and you want
it to encompass whatever use
cases it's actually trying to do
and yeah I feel like at
least with server components it strikes a decent
balance of like you're gonna think about this differently
it's not running in the client
yeah I think
sometimes
I don't know
maybe we'll come to regret this but I
think sometimes you
you know when people
talk about oh like I wish this was
more explicit
I think one thing we've noticed is that people
always say that in the beginning
and then six months later everyone is
like oh I want like a shortcut I want
to you know this term is too long or
it's like API name like I know what
it is already why do I have to type all
of this and so we
kind of I think we discount a little
bit of this initial knee-jerk reaction
because we just know yeah you know when
it's a common thing it's gonna feel different
like for example with use
like yeah I just gonna search for react use
that's gonna be like a top result in Google
because like we have enough
like mode to
you know to actually bubble up
so I think that helps
but it's also sometimes
sometimes you just
can't have an intuitive term because
the whole idea is different and
you might as well kind of
realize that
no this doesn't make sense I need to like
sit down and understand what this is about
none of my intuitions are
helping and like that's fine that's
because it's a new thing it is different
like it's good if you realize
that it's different
yeah I definitely think
it's signaling that but the
main thing people are wondering which I'm hoping
we can get through like with the live
coding today is like up until
now I've been able to just
spin up you know V or something like
that put a div with an ID of
main and hydrate a thing
in there and now we're basically saying
no there's there's more than that if you
really want to think about it this way having set
up my own service for
a week I can
say there is more to it and
I don't know if the react
team has any opinions on that right now of like
is DIY server components
something that's like does it matter
is it something we need or
is next.js just the way you should try it
yeah I think
so well there's
a bunch of different things there so
yeah I think like one thing
question yeah because like you kind
of alluded to this thing like I can
just like have a div and like put something
in there and so I think that
was more about not about
frameworks per se it was about like
client only versus
like build time or
SSR and so I think
like that's that's one question
the other question is like
do you know do it yourself
set up versus like a
framework or like should there be one
framework or many and I think that's that's a separate
question so which which one
which one of those do you want to go into
I'm more interested in the second one I guess
because the first one I've already
I pretty much agreed like yeah
I probably wouldn't point people to
just feed and react or
create react app to build something
I would if you're going to deploy it
anywhere I'm probably going to point you
to next.js or astro or
more likely next.js if you really want to
try server components
I think like on the first one my
perspective is that
and I mean that that's also
by you know we know that
the recommendation change was
pretty controversial
but we also didn't try to motivate it
like we do have like a deep dive there
that's like can I use react without the framework
sure yeah I think
it's a really nice documentation page
looking through it
the specific thing I think
that gets a bit lost is like
nobody
is you know it's not
about like the push
like the reason we don't suggest
Vite is
an option for you know you want to make
an app fully with react use Vite
like the reason we don't say this is
again because like default Vite
you know when you say Vite you probably
mean like a template that's blindside
only because if you use like a template
that has SSR and a bunch of other
stuff let's be real it is a framework
it's not a template
like it's an ad hoc framework
that is maybe a good framework but
if you compare it in terms of usage
community it's like a very
niche framework with you know
a very small community which is maybe
what you want but let's not fool ourselves
saying that this isn't
a framework and then if we talk
about like a default Vite setup with
this just like blindside
only the problem with this is
it's not that client
only is bad I don't think that's true
I think like for some cases it totally makes
sense it's more
that you're kind of
locking yourself into this
setup it's like let's say like later
you want to add a landing page
and you want the landing page
to have HTML in it and
because it's like it's silly not
to like why would you not have
HTML in a webpage
it's like it's better for SEO
sure like crawlers can understand
JavaScript but like not as fast
it's like better for
just like your users you don't have to
download the bundle to like show anything
and there are many
of these like benefits like you
you don't have like to spin up
like a separate project with like a static site
generator you just add a page
for this page you use
kind of you know static
static build whereas for
another page maybe you like opt
out and you return like
just a shell or like even
null for the server pass
for the build pass
then you do client only so it's
really about like encouraging you to use
a tool that lets you
even start with client only
but then the moment you want to have a page
or like a part of your
even enhance existing
pages
to be like generated at build time
or the server features
you don't have to migrate to another tool
you don't have to like redo your whole project
because your router wasn't designed
for this it's kind of like
it's also kind of like you used to put
the router inside
the you know your react app
and this is kind of like no the router
belongs outside
because if you put the router outside
then that lets you have like multiple
pages that are automatically
code split that have all these like different
optimization modes
it's really about like architectural question of pulling it out
so this is why
yeah this is why we don't recommend
the you know even though if you
want to do client side rendering only
that's fine but we do recommend
to do it in a way that lets you
enhance it with
build time or server logic later if you
want to
which kind of goes back to that point of like server
components can run in multiple ways
and you don't want a tool that just locks you
into one like I've definitely
had well at least for
most of the things I build I think this could
go on serverless if I just had
one query per RAM I could put this on something
and it would be way better and I don't
want to change frameworks to do that I just want to flip
a switch and this route is now on SSR
which is something a lot of
frameworks already do and it's
something like something like VEET
which is like a half framework
it's like a batteries included tool for
framework authors is how I kind of think
about it like you can go nuts
trying to build your own world inside of
VEET but the default is just like
sort of showing React on a workbench
without any opinions of where you put it
which for like
Ruby on Rails and stuff like that you're embedding a
React component in something that's fine and
I think the docs come out really well of like
if you have a stack right now here's
how you can put it in
as simply as possible wire up Babel
here you go but yeah
it lists out any other frameworks that
put those opinions on top so you
can deploy it somewhere which is
what 99% of people are going to do
even for like a hello world
yeah and
then like for your second question
about you know it should be like
should there be like a next only thing or
should there be many frameworks
or should you like do it yourself
I think it's still
an open question of what people will actually
want to do like I'm not sure
I think like personally I'd like
to see many solutions
I think there's like a
natural question of like how
tension there with differentiation
because
if you're a framework like if you look
at next app router API
you'll notice like a lot of
next APIs are kind of gone
so it kind of
feels more vanilla in a weird
way because it feels like
well there's no like gets that you know
there is
something for like static generation because it can
it can be handled directly but
there's no like gets
server side props it's just async
await right there's
you know like there's no like special APIs
for a bunch of stuff that used
to have special APIs
you know exports which is
like the big thing yeah
there are I think there are some
but you know for metadata and a few
other things that react doesn't handle
by itself but for
a bunch of things there isn't and
you can also compare it to remix I think
in like you don't render
an outlet you just accept children
which is like accepting children is
the most react
API possible it's like the most
vanilla thing and so
there's this question of like if
frameworks can and that was
the goal really with server components
is to get rid of
these framework concepts and kind of
fold them into react in a way that feels
vanilla and so
there's a question of like okay if other
frameworks
jump on the same train and try
to do a similar thing there
is a natural push to kind of
become more similar to
next app router maybe there's
ways to differentiate there like I don't
know but I think there
is like tension between
okay but how do you choose between frameworks then
if they're kind of
looking the same because we've
taken the primitives and like put
them into react
so I think that's something
that remains to be seen
but if
you compare it to like do it yourself
setup I think that's just kind of
exceedingly hard today and
it's mostly because server components
is a very futuristic
architecture I think maybe we
undersold like it
like for the bundling side
it relies on features that just don't
exist in bundlers today like
it has a whole you know like it
relies on a next generation bundler
and like a next generation router
and these things are being
built right now right like
we have some like we have
a backpack plugin that's like not very good
so some frameworks kind of
I wrestled it for a while I'm reading
commit messages from Sebastian like everything
is experimental like it's
very very experimental right now
if you want to DIY I actually got it working in ES
build because I reverse engineered what
the bundler is adding and I like
monkey patched it in which
like it's a way but I
agree like what it's doing is fundamentally
like it looks at each module
it figures out what it is and then
adds a lot of information and metadata so
we can like trace it back putting the client
components where they're supposed to go
and to set that all up yourself it's not as
simple as just like webpack
target JSX files react
plugin like there's
more to it yeah
I wouldn't say that the like I'd say
the bundler I think like
one thing I
I feel a bit
I think sometimes people
say oh it's so complicated
and I think if you really look at the ideas
the ideas are very simple it's just
that implementing them is complicated
because the tools were not designed for
these ideas so
if you think of the bundler integration
it's really about
supporting this use client directive
like that's a feature
with like one line
API it's not you know
it's not something that's like super
it's not some Java monstrosity right
it's a very simple idea
but the bundlers
like the today's generation
of bundlers was not designed
for this kind of feature
because it's like fundamentally different
it's on a similar scope
as you know if you went
back in time to like 2007
and was
trying to explain code splitting
to somebody who uses
if you
I don't know if you remember there was like require.js
which was like a bundler
that people used at the time
and I think like it didn't support
I don't think it supported code splitting
it was kind of loaded
like the optimizing bundler would put everything
into the same file
but it's a similar feature to like dynamic import
that lets you do code splitting
except it's like a different kind of
code splitting that splits apart
like the client parts
from the server parts
and so an ideal bundler would
treat all of this
as a single you know as a built in feature
and be able to
kind of process the
server tree and the client tree as like a
single pass with multiple
bundle outputs for different
targets and that's not something
that bundlers are great at today so
we can try to add it as plugins which is what
we've been doing but really ideally
you would redesign a bundler
around this idea and I think
you know TurboPack is like
one you know implementation
that currently treats it as a first class feature
and I think with time
other bundlers will and like I know
Devon from Parcel is also working on this
and I think with time we'll see
this feature adopted more broadly
and then I think we'll see
other libraries now that the feature
is in the bundlers I think we'll see
maybe Vue or
Svelte or others taking advantage
of that in like implementing similar
architectures on top of those features
yeah I actually
saw a stream yesterday with Evan Yu
who hopped on with Theo to talk
about what they're doing with Vite and Vue
and all of that and one part of that
discussion was Vapor which I believe
is like an early exploration of like what
could server stuff look like in
Vue and it doesn't mean Vaporware by the way
I'm hoping it doesn't anyways
but it's definitely
spreading right now and
if the creator of Vite is exploring
it that could mean it sort of
you know spreads out to anyone else
who's using Vite which as far as I know
is most frameworks that aren't Next.js
or Remix even Remix is
trying Vite as far as I know
so TurboPack for me is like a
wait and see I'm very curious about it
because I got to speak with Jared
a little bit in person
and it's definitely about like
build caching being very
focused on you know compiling
everything down to the very function
that you're trying to get and doing it
efficiently so I think
there will be sort of two competing
threads of like Vite is using
all the tech we have today and
TurboPack is kind of adapting Webpack
into something that could work
better tomorrow
I think TurboPack is
TurboPack is a completely new
codebase right it's not related to
Webpack so it's a rethinking
of
yeah it's complicated
because I heard the talk that said this is the
successor to Webpack even though it's
entirely different as far as
I can tell like I don't think it uses the same
config or conventions but
I haven't tried to use any of it yet
yeah I think it's successor just in the sense
that like Tobias
is working it so it's like
what did Tobias learn
from like I don't
know how many years of Webpack
and
yeah how do you design it again
now that you know all these lessons
which is kind of similar but you know with like
server components that's kind of what we've
seen and
I want actually to mention because
you know you were asking about the history and like
influences and for server
components it's really many
it's like it's our old
XHP stuff it's our
native stack that you know
works let's just do native
apps but driven by server
server driven UI
it's really so a lot of
a lot of contributions to server
components model came from Relay
and Joe Savona and
you know people on the Relay team
it was early exploration
like some of the earliest
design drafts were collaboration
with the Chrome team
and with
the Next.js team
so Next.js was kind of
because like get initial props was one
of the inspirations for this kind of API
so
that like we were kind of
like talking about it with Next.js team a long
time ago and so it's really
it's unifying many
many branches and there's
a lot you know there's a lot that we were
inspired by while working
on it. Yeah
and I kind of let that GraphQL point drop
earlier but it's a really
I never made that parallel but it makes
sense of like it has that same
goal of only send data to the
client that is necessary
in order to render what's on the page
and today like if you want to render
anything you can optimize your
API as hard as you can to make sure
it only sends the data that you want
but people kind of realize GraphQL is hard
to set up sometimes it's too heavy weight
so if there was a way that basically filters
it out for you where you're writing
your own back end to grab that data
and just hydrate the little pieces you want down
the chain like that's oddly
a successor to that idea
of like making sure all
the data you send down is actually lightweight
and I'm curious if we'll ever
end up with dev tools around I'm sure we will
end up with dev tools around that but
it's something I've never really thought about is like
how big are my props like I'm probably
sending a ton of props right now and I have no idea
what it is and the easiest thing
is to just send all the props
but if there was a way to debug like
your props bundle is like 10 kilobytes
of JSON are you sure you wanted to do that
like I think that would really make
server components start to make even more sense
yeah it's
pretty tricky
I think like the whole
kind of monitoring story
like the other piece
of the puzzle there is
you don't really have much
like you don't have a network timeline
for the server which
I think makes people anxious like
oh is it going to have so many waterfalls
and like you can have waterfalls
you know with something like Remix too
like it's actually pretty trivial
to have one
but it's not obvious like
I think if we had better tooling
for just visualizing
what actually happens on the server
how did your requests get processed
I think that would ease a lot of this anxiety
and it would also be useful
for other frameworks like it's not
server component specific
so I think like we need a lot more
like I think the
kind of the optimizations and developer
experience would get like
a lot better when we have better
observability into
what happens on the server
and what crosses the boundary
yeah and like what is contributing
to that like which components have
really like
you know a lot of output and then
you're like okay let's make this one client
component and then increases
the bundle size a bit but then we don't have to send
the stuff it generates
on like every navigation
but that's also the beauty of this paradigm is you can
you know you can flip it back and forth
you can flip it back and forth
yeah I remember for that space I was like
that's the one thing Astro doesn't do very well
because it's like you use styling
or you can do styling differently which can get
in the way I also do want to shout out
Joshua who rated and
apparently works at Code Academy as well
he was chiming in a bit
oh I tried to shout out but it said it doesn't exist
sorry go follow Joshua everyone
but he was saying like
yeah definitely run into the
big props bundle at Code Academy
of like the slowdowns were really just
slamming a bunch of data down the pipe that
didn't need to be and it was just delaying
the amount because it had to
get initial props which was a lot
and then hydrate it all onto the page
and there was no way to sort of
introspect that like
because you're on the client you're not really introspecting
what your server is doing
when you're on that boundary
yeah so the other thing that maybe
is not obvious but you know when I
talk about server components
also including like
10 years of hard thinking about
optimizations it's also stuff like this
so like with server components
you don't actually have
this kind of waterfall
where like in
traditional server rendered
React frameworks including
Next.js you would have this
you have to download all the code
then like
enough to hydrate your page
like the main chunk
you have to get all the data
like inlined into HTML
and only then you can start hydrating
so server components doesn't work like this
in server components you only need
like enough to
get the initial shell
to hydrate so actually
your components
your client component chunks
they're loaded asynchronously
and so React can start hydrating
before all the data arrives
before all the code arrives
we actually want to start as early as possible
and then we kind of
make a tree interactive
as like chunks of code
chunks of data
streaming, they're like separated
if you see like how Next
kind of generates the stuff
it emits separate script tags
that add a little bit more data
as it becomes available
and we update the UI
even before React actually loads
we're able to update the UI to progressively show
more output from the server
it's all designed to be very
incremental so that you don't
have these things where you have to do
the whole pass
of one thing and then the whole pass
of another thing it's like you do small bits
here and there so it progressively
becomes more and more interactive
yeah exactly
and I think that's a good segue into
a little bit of code that I have to
demo that's outside of Next.js
so
it looks like you can still see my live share
but I'll start
by giving a little context on
what we might try to build today
it's meant to have multiple
steps so if we don't get to all of them
we at least have something at the end of the day
but let me also
screen share for the lovelies out there
guest screen share, cool
so
this is just a basic mockup
that I put together of something you might
try to build when you're building
an application. I called it
abramix as a pun on abramov
I tried, I really tried here
sorry about that
well thank you
but this is like a basic song
interface you might have where
you just have a readout of all of your albums
you might have a search bar that filters
which albums are showing on the page
and I'd love to talk about how would you
do search, where would you do that logic
client versus server since
I've wondered that a lot
and maybe you
have individual routes for every album
where you click into one, it goes to
slash album name and then it shows you
more information and that can be
client side routing
we use Next.js for that
I think it's a pretty clear
upgrade journey
but as a workbench
to try that out I have
a server running over here
on what I called simple
RSC which is a
repo that people can go try out now
if they want to, it only runs on node
version 18.13
because I'm bad at testing things before I
deploy, but if you want to
try it out, it's just a node
server that builds
some React components using esbuild
and lets you see
a single route on the page, there's no
routing, there's no opinions around really
anything, all that's coded into this
is a way to write a server component
and a debugging view
at the bottom of the page that shows
you all of the stuff that is
coming down from the server as the page
is rendering in real time
and you can see a basic example
of that off to the right
where we have our server
component over here in our editor
there's some stale imports that we're not using
right now, but all this is doing
is it's creating a server component
it's rendering an h1 saying
welcome to server components
oh is the repo still private, oh dang
thank you for the call out
let me
make my screen share and change it to public
so I don't dox myself
and then I will show it again
if I go to settings
change visibility, change to public
I want to make this repository
public, please please
please, I have to send an
SMS to myself to make it public
oh my god
there's three dialogues
and a text message, that's crazy
okay, now
it should be public, if anyone wants to
click on that link
you can go try it out
and now I have to go back
to code, hold that up
and send in the chat
alright
but yeah, I heard your opinions
earlier of like, you're probably not going to
do this to do anything production ready
which is why I only set this up with the dev
server, I only set it up with
a panel of everything
that's going on, and there's no way
to actually deploy this to production right now
because that's not really the intended use case
but yeah, off to
the right is the most user-friendly
feed that I could create
and it is literally
showing you all of the stuff that is coming down the
wire when you stream something
so here, what we're rendering on the page
is just some instructions
as I would call them, from the server
to go make some JSX DOM elements
and then append them to the page
as we're seeing here, and there's no
hydration or server rendering going on, it's just like
a client that fetches a server
component and shows it to you
yeah, first
do you have any initial questions on
this setup and everything that I have going on
because there is a lot under the hood
are you asking
me or the viewers?
a little bit, just to
slow down for a second
no, no, I'm saying, is it a question
to me, do I have questions, or are you
asking somebody?
yeah, maybe one thing
I'm not sure about
is
how did you get the build setup?
you said you did your own
bundle plugin
yes, I did
so, the build
is actually pretty interesting
it's inside of this handler.js
file, and this is going
right in the weeds, but I don't really mind it
where
I set up a simple
request response handler, that's all this is
it just takes in a web standard request
sends a response, and
in order to get the server
I set it up to import
a built server
and the bundle map is
something that's generated separately, as it
crawls through the page, it discovers client
components, and puts them into this map
that it's able to match up at the end of the day
that gets into client components
which I guess we'll explore in a moment
but that's all it really
does for that, the more interesting
file, actually I just remembered
that I moved the build step out
over here
I can jump over here, but this
is using esbuild to do everything
so not necessarily plugins, but
it's got a two step
build process right now
where it looks for that server component
and it will output it
just using a JSX transform
it's not going to resolve any modules or anything
it's literally just going to output it
with the JSX transform, leave everything else alone
and the one weird piece
is this part right here
anyone watching at home, don't do
this, but I am reading
the file, whenever it discovers
a client component, I'm checking for
the use client directive
and I'm doing this wild line
right here that
inserts a few things that Webpack
looks for in order to decide if something
is a client component
so it imports it inline
it tells it that it's a client
reference, and then it returns
that in order to import onto the page
and I figured out
it works! It's not using Webpack
and it still does technically work
but that's an under the hood view
I'm sure you don't have
pleasant opinions about it, but
it works
I think I don't fully understand
the handler part
this runs
what is the
oh sure
why is there a
path, oh so this is the thing
you fetch, right?
this is the thing you fetch
yeah, so this is
the server components endpoint
so to speak
yeah, and I could have
it's a bit confusing because
it looks like I'm
fetching JSX and I'm like
what is this about?
I named it that thinking that's how it worked
and realized that's not what I'm doing
I'm actually sending you the stream
I'm not sending you the file
this is kind of more like
like RSC or
yeah
it's just like an API
it's like a
GraphQL endpoint I think, except
instead of GraphQL it's like
React
okay, now that makes sense, I get it
yep, I should have explained that part
because I realized after the fact that's not
what it is, and I also looked through
some of the React docs and
the content type of what this sends down is
like X component is
one way to put it, it's special
it's something that React understands
is the way that I would put it
yeah, okay
that sounds good
yeah, I don't
think I have any more questions
so we can
maybe try to do something
I do want to clarify
though for people watching that
if I understood correctly what you're saying
like, the architecture here essentially
is that the browser
will load like an empty HTML shell
which is kind of like
a traditional CRA app actually
like a web app
it loads empty HTML
then requests the
server component endpoint
and server component streams in
you know, what the server output is
so it's not super efficient because
it has this client-server waterfall
for the first load
whereas a proper setup would
actually do SSR as well
so it would
do that on the server instead
like when it hits index.html
it would
actually talk to the RSC endpoint
on the server
load that HTML, stream the HTML
to the client, and that's how the
initial page would be
actually have content without
an extra waterfall
but this is much harder to do
manually, and there's already enough
of manual setup, so this is just
the simplified version
yeah, and that's the callout
that's definitely worth making
because I'll admit, I tried, but I realized
doing that without blocking
on suspense boundaries
and not just reading the whole stream
I was like, I can't, I don't know
what I'm supposed to do here, I know
Next.js knows, they figured it out
but yeah, it's a different
problem
it's doable, like we actually have
an example in the React repo
so we go to fixtures slash
flight, it has like a super
believe me, I've had
every page visited at this point
yeah, so it shows
how to do it, but it is confusing
it's a lot
oh yeah, for a client
emulator, this is the page that
I was reading for a little bit
I don't actually see
because I think you're sharing just the part of the screen
so I don't know
I shared an individual tab
which means I would have to visit it in this
tab, and then it would work
it also
might be delayed
yeah
this is the weird part, and this
definitely speaks to what you said about client
isn't really browser
client is just whoever wants to consume
that server component, and it could
be the server itself in order to render it
to HTML, or it could be the client
when you're trying to do client-side routing
which is usually what you'd end up with
here, like yeah, the initial load
of, now I have to hit back
the initial load of this
that's not good, you want to have the server rendered
but if I want to load this as
another route coming in, then
it actually makes sense, I actually want to get this
full stream and just render it onto the page
of JavaScript
yeah, I think another thing that's
worth highlighting maybe is
I think
sometimes people have this
wrong mental model of
when you have a server component in the tree
you go to the server, and it's
like each individual server component
is kind of rendered independently
but it's really not like this
it's more like
it's just, there's
I think in a simple setup, like
the one you have, the only
server component that you talk
to or render is the
top-level one, so it's really about
top-down rendering
the whole page, and if you
refetch, it's going to go to the
server component
server and re-render the
app, the top-level thing
and get the new output for that
and then that's of course not super
efficient, so this is why with something
like Next.js, you have nested routing
where the granularity
is to the
sub-route level
so you can't update
one small server component
that doesn't make sense in the model, because they
all have to be consistent
with each other, but what you can do
is you can invalidate the sub-route
so that would be like, for example, if you have
a shell of the page, and then they have
some kind of tab interface
like about, photos,
memories, whatever,
then when you switch those things,
it's just this part that
gets independently refetched
from the server, but if you want
to refetch something
broader, like you want to change
there's a mutation that affected something
else on the screen, you just refetch
the whole thing, and this might sound like
oh, this is going to be super slow, but let's remember
that this is literally what happens if the
user just opens the page and
opens the tab, so it's not
that different from
traditional web models.
Yeah, it's not.
And that is a real big thing of like
routes aren't necessarily
full routes, they're layers of an
onion or individual components
that you can just slot into view
like this server component that we've created
here, this could be fetched from
some other route on the page, and it could just add
welcome to server components below
a navigation bar and other things
that are being rendered. It's just a way to
officially fetch server stuff.
Yeah, but then for that you kind of
need a framework because
implementing this kind of nested thing
in this demo, that's yet
another level of complexity, and that's why
DIY is
actually really hard today because you just
don't have a router like this
that's, you know, there is no RSC
router you can use off the shelf.
But you can build one.
You can write one.
I'm not going to invite myself to do that.
I've already sunk too much time into this.
But yeah, that's
why I guess the main goal of this project
was like, I just want a way to workbench
one server component and have a
dev panel of the stuff coming down the pipe.
And that's it. Like, no opinions
on routing because, as you kind of mentioned,
React is
I don't know if you said this yet, but React
is more of an architecture
and a library than it is a
framework. And in
order to have any opinions about, like, where
do the routes go? What is the
nesting strategies that you probably
want? Like, that's immediately framework
opinions. And that's already taking
things to a new space.
Yeah.
So with this, I'm thinking
like, maybe we can put some albums
on the page and render them out to start.
I have some
really basic endpoints here.
And this is literally just
fetching some JSON. And I say
fetch, it's just an
import with an artificial
wait time to make it feel like it's a server
but it's not. It was just
the easiest way.
Where should that be looking? I'm not sure.
Sorry. Right.
I was just looking at this DB fetch file.
Oh, okay.
This part isn't too important
but I just made some JSON dumps
of good albums that I
like. That's why I actually mentioned
earlier, like, if you want to put an album on here, we can.
Because you put out those really
good tweets of just, like, a random song on Spotify.
Like, this is great. Like, you know
what, you're right. It's really good.
But yeah, that's all this is
doing. I have a get all, which will
wait 300 milliseconds and send you all the
albums. And get by ID, where
you can pass in an individual ID
slug, whatever you want. So if you
want to do routing, that's how you would get, like,
an individual entry.
But yeah.
I hopped back over here. I think I have to
keep, like, focusing you to bring you
into the model. Yeah, yeah.
We're trying VS Code live share, by the way.
So
we'll see how it goes.
Anything goes
is the idea here. If we want to jump
in and type code, either one of us can do it.
But yeah.
In order to render all of the albums
onto the page,
well, I've already kind of done it.
I kind of spoiled it.
Where in a server company, you can just
say, wait, get all the albums,
and then to put them on the page, I guess we could just
do a map over whatever's
going on.
There's one thing I asked about earlier
where I was wondering
why you would need an
ID prop or a key. That's what
I'm thinking of.
Because that's always been the thing with React
Lists that I forget.
Which is adding a key onto every entry.
So is that still
required? And if so,
what is sort of the benefit to that?
Yeah, so maybe
I think to answer that question,
do you know why it's required?
If we put server components out of the
story, do you know why it's required on the client?
Yeah, I know why it's required
on the client. Usually for
if the list updates
and you need things to
reorient and you want it to re-render
efficiently, then a key will actually tell
React, this is the part that was removed.
This is the part that got moved up.
So if you want to animate that transition
of the
item with a key of 4 moved
from this position to this position,
React can track, oh, that's
the thing with the key of 4. I know how to animate
that up if you're using some external
library for it. Is that kind of right?
I know there's more reasons.
Sort of. I think maybe the focus
on efficiency is a mistake.
I think we've kind of maybe explained
it badly in the old docs where
we explain it as, oh, if
you want it to be fast, then you should use
a key. It has nothing to do with being
fast.
Yeah, not fast.
Just to do it at all.
If you want to do it in transition.
Well, I don't think it has to do with animations
either. It's
really
about
kind of identity
across re-renders.
So it's
about state. And I don't mean just
React state. I mean even
input state.
If you just render an input
that's uncontrolled
or focus or
scroll position or any
of the things that are kind of
stateful,
it's about
like imagine you render
a list of components
and then each of those components has
an input inside. And again,
this input doesn't have to be
controlled value
proper or anything like this. It could just be
browser input, React doesn't touch it.
You could do whatever with it.
And so you type into each of those
inputs and then suppose
the first item in the
list was deleted. And so
there's a re-render and
React now sees that
there's the
item, like you're
rendering two items instead
of three. The first one is gone.
And so if you don't provide the key,
React has no idea which of
these items correspond.
How do the old items kind of
match to the new ones?
Because it could be like this.
But it could be like this.
So it can't
know which one was deleted
because it
just doesn't have the knowledge.
And so if you get
it wrong, so if it just tries to
for example, it just matches up
like this.
And that's the default.
It goes in the direction.
This is the first one, used to be here,
now it's here. This is the second one, used to be here,
now it's here.
So the inputs
will be preserved.
And so if what
actually happened is this,
so the first item got deleted,
then you're going to see
wrong inputs at wrong positions.
And that is really the issue.
If you've already modified them,
but then things shifted, you're just
going to see
it's kind of the same.
Imagine you're in a bus
and there's like
20 people in the bus and
everybody has
a seat.
And you leave
some stuff on your seat. Maybe you leave your
headphones on the seat. I've done that once
and they disappeared.
And so imagine
the situation.
You leave the bus.
When you come back to the bus,
you want to go to your seat, even
if there's fewer people. Even if some people
got off the bus, you want to remember which
seat is yours. You don't want to
sit somewhere else. And so what happens
if you don't specify a key,
it's like you don't know what
your seat is.
So by
default, you're going to be seated in
the order.
That's kind of the default for the key. It's just like index.
So it's like the first people who gets
on the bus goes to the first seat.
The second person
goes to the second seat and so on.
And so if one of the people has
left, then everybody
else will get the wrong seat because
the order has shifted. And that's why
you need keys.
And so it's the same with
server components. You don't notice it all the time.
But I've definitely run into
why can't you just use the index
in the array? It's like, well, if you do that,
you actually get a clearer idea of why
keys are bad or why
you need a key. Where if you remove
the first item in the list, now
all of a sudden, item 0 became 1,
item 1 became 2, item 2 became
3. So it's like they're all different people
now. It's like everyone on the bus
traded seats all of a sudden
when that actually didn't need to happen.
And you don't always notice it.
But with efficient libraries, it's like you do.
Yeah, so this is very interesting
because you don't always notice it.
And like one
way to notice it is, yes, animations,
because they make it obvious that, wait,
a thing disappearing is a
very different thing from, you know, things
reordering and updating.
But another way to notice
it is, and that is
the most insidious thing, it's like
initially you don't add a key because
it seems to work fine. And then
like five months later,
somebody adds a little bit piece
of state somewhere deep down
in the item components,
like even like five levels down.
And this piece
of state will get misplaced when they
reorder because you didn't give the right key
to the top level thing.
So it's like if everybody leaves the bus
but nobody has headphones on the seat,
the seats kind of don't matter.
It's okay to sit anywhere. But if
you start leaving your valuables,
now it becomes
important. So that's why, and sometimes
index as a key is fine
when that actually corresponds to
the identity. So it's like
literally it's important, you know, the first thing
is the first thing, the second thing is the second.
That's what, you know, like a list of
words in a sentence or something
like this, or like the first line
of code, the second line of code.
Then it kind of makes sense that, yeah, the index
is actually the identity
of that thing. It makes sense that
the, you know, so.
Yeah, I agree.
But I'll say specifically
the server components part of this is
it's important for server components too
because server component output can
be refreshed. So if you have
for example like a refresh
button that will
cause, you know, the server component output
to update, maybe you deleted
that album from the database and they're all
going to like shift by one. And so this
is again why you want to have a key.
Yeah, that's the
part that I like, I don't know what it looks like
because I've only played with server components
in a read only model
where it's like I funnel all my data down
it renders on the page and
any mutations beyond that are
handled with client. And
it sounds like there are ways
with server components to like sort of
refresh, refetch
like the same fragment of components
and actually have it re-render
like server only search or something like that.
Yeah, that's exactly the
point. Like you're not supposed to be
copying, you know, props
from the server into state and then like
updating that state. Like the
whole point is not to have to do that
and to just be like something changed
just like you refresh
an API call except here you refresh
the output.
Yeah, exactly. And I do
want to try that. We might have to move to Next.js
to try it, I have no idea.
But we'll just see.
But I think that also speaks to like what
we're getting over here.
So what I did is
I just rendered out the album titles
as list items and
the immediate thing that
you sort of notice in that dev panel
at the bottom is
it's not passing down the entire
list of albums. It's only passing
down a set of like instructions
to like write out
the name with the ID and that's
it. Like there's no images in here,
there's no albums that we weren't
searching for. Well, I guess we're getting all of them.
But there's also a big list of songs
that could have been sent down the wire.
But because we're doing all these
instructions on the server, it's only
going to send this. We basically wrote our own
GraphQL query in a way of like
get album and just the title
field and then render that
into something.
Yeah, I would maybe slightly reframe
what you're saying instructions
and it's kind of correct in a way
but it is a bit
I think like there's a way to misinterpret it
where you think the server is kind of sending
commands whereas
the mental model is more like
the server just sends a response
that's essentially
you can think of this response
as it's almost like JSON.
So it's almost like a big
JSON tree that
includes your
kind of your HTML
components, like your React
components, you know like things like
native and so on except
formatted as JSON
kind of like the virtual DOM
as well as like if you have client components
it will send also render
this like like button with these
props and so these props are also
going to be kind of like JSON, right?
So you can imagine the response as
just like big JSON object
except that would not be efficient because then
you would have to wait for that entire
object before you can like start
rendering it properly
Our protocol is just
a thing that splits this JSON into
parts. It's like JSON
with holes. So it says like here's
a hole that's going to be filled in later
and so they're sent as
they become available it sends more
and more. But conceptually it's more
like you know
filling in the remaining content. It's
not so much like it's not imperative
as like do this then do this.
It's just filling in the parts as
they become available.
Yep. Yeah I kind of say instructions
where it's like React is going to
take this blob and convert it
to JSX which becomes
actual like DOM queries to
render stuff on the page. But
I agree it's like
it's not just the data
it's the HTML
in a different shape. It's actually
filtering out what needs to be rendered
based on well what are you trying to
render? Like you're not going to use
we're not going to send the album image down the pipe
because you didn't render an image. You never
accessed it. So it's not sending
down like the album object. It's sending down
the values that have been
put in there.
I'm curious. Do you want to
kind of
show what happens if
we
if we kind of split it into the components
so that you can
delay. So you can send. Okay
yeah let's do that.
Let's see it.
I mean I can type
it out since I think all we have to do is this.
So now I'm going to make
a separate albums call and
Perdo's curious like
you know a wait is always going to be
a blocking thing. It's not going to send
this until this is done.
So if you wanted to
you know delay that or control
when this runs you can move the query
somewhere else or even pass down the promise
as a prop which is something that I've
seen the experiments with.
And in here I'm going
to just pass down the list
without the other stuff.
And do you want me
to put a suspense around this or just put
albums. Let's maybe start
with just albums and then we'll add
suspense and see how it changes
things. Okay. Oh it's
thinking that's the thing.
There we go.
Too helpful.
And don't worry about the
squiggle. That's just because
it doesn't know about async being a thing.
I know that's like a patch you can
make in next JS.
But yeah what we get here.
I think you want to get rid of this line too right.
Oh you're totally right.
Yeah.
Okay that's better.
So now yeah everything comes down in
one chunk it looks like.
And this isn't split perfectly.
This was supposed to split out like this
part from this part. I'm still trying to figure out how
to parse it because sometimes things come so
quickly it's like part of the same message.
But generally
what you're going to get is like you're going to get
the welcome to server components and then
immediately you're going to get
the next chunk and
you're going to load in tandem.
Yeah so what I want to call attention to
can I
like yeah.
So what I want to call attention to is like this
protocol that you're showing in the dev panel
like that's an implementation detail
so it's not actually something you're supposed to
be able to like read or care about
except for I don't know maybe some kind of debugging
but mostly if you're debugging
React like if you're working on React yes
that's useful but it's not something we want
you to kind of think about and it's going to change
over time it's not you know it's not
super optimized yet.
But if we're
using it as an instructional tool
you know to kind of teach how this works
I think it's interesting to notice
yeah I see your formatting
is a bit messed up because you see it says
0 colon blah blah
blah and then it says 1 colon blah blah
blah I think those were supposed to be separate
lines because like in the response
there are separate lines
but I want you to notice how it's
structured like do you notice
it's like
0 is like the first line
and it says at 1
and I don't remember the exact syntax again
that's not the point but it kind of references
like this is a hole it says like
the result of 0 is
going to be streamed under
number 1 and then you see like number
1 says you need
to have like a header with
welcome to server components
and then the rest is going to be streamed under
number 2 you see it says like
L2 is like I don't remember
what L means but it says
that that's going to be coming later and then
2 is like the remaining response
and so these are these like
that's the key thing that makes it possible
to stream parts because we just leave
holes and we're like yeah this thing
number 42 is going to be filled in later
and then we're able to like stream
that part
yep and yeah I agree
like you're not going to be looking at this
I didn't really care about the formatting so much
as like what data is coming down
and what's the order
like this data came down a second later
why and
yeah the dev tools are split up by like
the order to stream comes in
and I don't split it up by these like numbers
but that's the indicator
that's where the holes are which is probably what you're looking
for if you're thinking like
first bit is this second bit is this
and you can see like 2 matches up with 2
and all that stuff
maybe if I add the
pre wrap
or whatever the CSS thing to preserve
new lines maybe then it will
split 0 and 1 because
0 and 1 are I think they arrive
in the same response chunk
but they are like separate lines
they're separate things
but it doesn't matter
it doesn't matter
and sometimes changes where it's like
I decided this chunk should load with
the next one and sometimes it's like no it's more
efficient to put it up here so there's some
optimization going on but
in this example am I right
that at least as
the user sees it you're going
to see all of this stuff coming in
at once like you're not
going to see like one then the next
exactly
and the idea here is
the way you structure
your
the way you decide
which components do what kind of data
fetching and like moving
data fetching calls between them should not
affect the visual output for
the user because
I think that is like
there's a bunch of things we've learned that
we haven't communicated super well
but I think like this is one of them
like you want to have the freedom to move
the data fetching code around
without any effect on the
user experience or like the way
the user perceives it and then
you want the people who are not necessarily
super skilled
in like how data fetching
works like you know like a designer
to be able to
say I want like this piece
of JSX to have its own
loading indicator
like its own skeleton
and to be able to do that completely
declaratively just by
you know putting it into JSX
tree without worrying about
how you know how it's
how it's actually kind of streamed
in so the
way the loading the progression
the loading sequence that
the user sees
like the visual loading sequence
is completely decoupled
from you know the
the streaming sequence because
for streaming we want to stream as
much as we can as early as we
can as we discover things
but then you know to the user we
want to present them like each visual state
should be intentional and only
correspond to what the user actually wants to see
Yeah and definitely
seeing that here and I know that
as you sort of cascade down
multiple fetch calls it's
really just going to wait for everything before
going to the user if you aren't suspending
if you aren't doing anything like that
it's just going to bunch up all of those requests
and you can do a promise.all at the top
level if you really want to be smart
about like parallelizing each fetch
but that's exactly what
we're seeing here of like even though it's in the second
one it's all going to come down in one
big chunk and I alluded
to how you could avoid that
but well okay I say avoid
as if it's a bad thing this is actually
the behavior you probably do want
but if there is
like behavior
when would you say like
is a good use case for
wrapping something in a suspense boundary
it's probably pretty nuanced but
I'm curious if you have thoughts about
like where you found it. Yeah I would just say
like if it feels slow
because you have a slow data source
or there's
a lot of logic that needs to be downloaded
it's like suspense also
works for client
like it's integrated with everything
right like we're going to integrate it with CSS
we're already integrating it with images
so it's already
integrated with code it's like if you
render a like button component
it's a client component and the suspense
is going to wait automatically
for that client code
to load even if it's code split
like it is code split by
default like if you import a client
component from a server component
it's like there is no
need to do code splitting it's just code splitting
is how it works and so it's
going to wait for that
code and any data and
in the future like CSS or images
to be ready and then
it flips you know it makes it visible when like
all the things in that tree resolve
so I think pragmatically speaking
it's just you have something that loads
that takes a bit of time you don't know why
it takes a bit of time but actually it doesn't matter
you just wrap it in suspense
and that kind of lets you unblock
the rest it's like here's a slow
part I have some
I asked the designer like I am the
designer I designed some visual skeleton
for that thing I'm just going to plug
it in here
yeah I think that's really
cool that y'all are just seeing is like any
slow data source no matter what it is
I don't know what it would look like to say like
wrapping a style
sheet in suspense
or something like that but
that would be more
automatic so if you imagine
for example a component
imports like a
CSS module or something like this
and or
like some kind of static CSS
and JS with like static extraction
then you could imagine
a compiler or like a framework
would put the link
tag for the style sheet
into component output automatically
and then the React would know to
wait for that CSS to
load before it can display the
component it would put the link tag into
the head or something like this
so it would be automatic it's not something you think about
but it's just
it's just better than the
current best practice of
like either you load
all CSS in the beginning
for like the entire app or
you do some kind of
you do some kind of split
in but then JavaScript can't
even start executing
for like independently of CSS
because like they're grouped together
and like you want
to have this ability of start executing
JavaScript even before CSS loads
but then hold back
the rendering until we actually
have the CSS so that the user doesn't
see unstyled content so this
would be automatic or another example
is like you have an image tag
for example of like profile cover
and you might want to kind of hold
back showing the thing
until you have the image
you know unless it's like super slow or
like there would be like a way to opt out
so you would be don't wait for this image
yeah that's the clearer one
to me because I would love to have an API
that's like suspense
suspense fallback
like blurred image
and then inside of this
is like the real image
that we're going to wait on
and that's conceptually what it's doing I'm sure
you wouldn't just pass in blurred image
but it would be
it's that hook
to not ship like
the massive Gatsby image component to the client
that does all of these fancy fetches
like it's just telling the server
stream in the blurred image then stream
in the regular image when you're done
yeah that's one way to do it
but I think like it also
it doesn't necessarily have to do with
blurred images like I think you can
think of this like blurred images
as a kind of next level
optimization that you could do
but just the capability of
being able to say
like don't show until this image
is ready
like wait for it
to pop in
and then that could be a blurred one
if you want to make it
you know like faster
or it could be that you actually
wait for the whole thing
you know with a normal
image but then you do have blurred one
as like a placeholder so it really depends
on like how you put it so
we'll see but the capability
like the important part is just like
it would be hooked up automatically
to the suspense so suspense
would act as you know you
declaratively specify this is
what I want to see if something
inside is not ready and then something
could be like data, it could be code
it could be images, it could be stylesheets
it's like anything asynchronous can
work and you don't have to like do it
in your head all the time
yeah
and that does feel like the message I've been
getting from Next.js where it's like you know
don't worry about deployment target
that's automatic with how you're doing your fetch
calls, don't worry about
image optimization, just use the defaults
and it'll load in the correct
like webp, avif, whatever
because
these are decisions like
we can make when there's a problem
but a vast majority of the time
we don't need to make it ourselves
like there is a default that the framework
knows about and it can probably just go ahead
and do it
yep
yeah and I also never demo what this actually
does and I'm realizing these annotations
are completely wrong, I'm going to revisit this
but the main thing
that we're getting over here is like
we get our welcome to server components
and then a flash of fetching albums
until the albums come down
and then the only difference in the
response is that now we have
this like react suspense
idea where what I'm assuming
happens is like if
it is wrapped in suspense
it's going to say alright here's that hole
that you mentioned, here's that
separate component that you're going to
slot in when it comes down the pipe
but I have a fallback for you while you're waiting for
that, don't like block rendering
the whole page to the browser, actually
go ahead and render everything before this
show this fallback
and then L3 is going to match up with this 3
that comes down 300
milliseconds later based on how we have it set up
so it's just letting the server
like show something in the meantime
and stop blocking if it was actually an issue
maybe you can increase the delay
a little bit and then it would be
more obvious because it's kind of
really fast now
yeah and if it
I know, and if your delay is that
low you probably don't need suspense
I don't really know what the threshold is but you feel it out
so I set it up here
let's see what that does
did it not
oh I don't think it's watching, that's the issue
yep I think my
file watcher is only looking at source
but yeah there we go, now we
see like a full 2 second delay
maybe it's getting from like the Discogs
legacy API which is
slow, I've used it before
but yeah
now you get like fetching albums
maybe it's a beautiful skeleton that you designed
and then the 3 is going to become
this 3 as soon as it's ready
but now we have a fallback so it doesn't have to
wait on it
yep
cool stuff
so I mean that's a basic demo
of like suspense and fallbacks
I
well one thing I can do is
actually top this off with an image
on the top and then
I was curious to get into how I could
generate a search bar for this
and what would be involved in that
and I'll go ahead and do
I think album.
what do I call it, cover?
autocomplete
alt
that
album.title again
that should be good
now, well I'm going to
oh god there's no styling
let me see here
I tossed tailwind on top of this thing
just to make us move a little bit faster
so let's say class name
with like
20 just so we don't have to worry about that
let's see that
oh yeah way better
and also turn off the delay
so we can start working on this more easily
there we go
okay and now in our
server response now we're going to get the image
but before it's just not going to serialize
what you don't use
which is kind of the beauty of it
so yeah from here
how could I set up
a search filter that does it
maybe server side, maybe client side
yeah
so that's really
your choice
that's kind of the fun thing about it
you can do it either way
and there are different tradeoffs
so for example
if you have the entire list
let's say the thing
we're talking about is
it's mostly going to have maybe 50 albums
or something like this, you want to always load them all
then maybe
it makes sense to do client search because
well then it will be instant
so it would be, we could just filter on
the client and show the results
and that's one way we could go about it
on the other hand if you have
thousands of albums and they're
paginated or whatever
and you don't want to download them all
to the client
then it makes sense to make the search driven by
the server and just
pass down the
update the URL
as you actually do
each time you write into the input
you do a router navigation
through a different query
and then on the server you read the query
and you refresh
you just send the new output
so maybe we could do it both ways
and just compare them
how do you feel about that?
Yeah, we can
I don't know if the server way will work without
page refreshes
we have the Next.js
escape hatch in this repo
I put a Next app right up here
so if we need to we can just drag this in
I'm hoping
but yeah, I think starting with clients is a good idea
because we didn't even demo client yet
or how it even works
so I can make a separate file
for that
.jsx
and try to call you in here
and at the top
you just put use client
and sure
no
but close
well this will be
a search box so in this example
it would pass through all of the
album info as props I'm assuming
right? Where it comes from the server
and this is just
what do you want, like what component structure
do you have in mind? I think I'm not fully
understanding what do you
want to put where?
Yeah, so
the typical way that I would do it
is this is a client component
it receives the get
all result from the server
so all the albums come in here
and then it has a form input
that will filter what's showing
and then it would render what?
It would
render either
all the albums or the results
like if your input's blank it would show all
of them and then as you start typing it would
filter based on the title
Yeah, I think I just got confused
by the file name because it's like album
but I think it's essentially like searchable
list or something like this
Yeah, I think
that's a good idea
searchable, yeah searchable list
is fine
You like short names
I do, sometimes
I either go really short like
search or really long like searchable album
list. Yeah, searchable album list
is nice
like on the homepage
I don't know if you've noticed like on the React homepage
we have kind of a progression of
examples building up
and like it starts with like video
then there's video list then there's like searchable
video list and then there's
like conf page or something like this
so it's actually about
the canonical example we picked
so that's kind of funny that
we're doing that now
Yeah, I mean it works
Oh, that's cool that it's called searchable
Yeah, I've never said searchable
I would probably say like album list search
but yeah
But then it sounds like the search is just
like I think the thing that's confusing about it
is it seems like it's just the
yeah
Yeah
and so it's so hard to
name your Lego bricks
but this will work
So yeah, search and set search, that's fine
and we're not going to use
like an actual search library for this
it would just be
well that's, yeah, you could just do it like this
and this
is really good actually
Dang it Copilot, you took all the fun out of it
but that is it, that works fine
So
Well no, that's actually not very good
It's not a very good version
because it
it would search in the middle
of the words, right
so if you
Oh sure
I can, let me copy and paste
I have a version that I
that I wrote for
for the React homepage
that I can
I can actually
just copy and paste it
so this
is the
yeah let me
copy and paste it here except that's going to be
filter albums, that's going to be
albums
that's, that you called this thing
search, so I'll call this thing search as well
and then
the, what is the
what is the
we care about title and about
what is the other thing
that we care about
Artist? It's just the title
That's another field
Artist, maybe
Yeah, but does it have
does it have artist in the album
info somewhere, like what's the structure
Yeah, and I can
actually, I set this up with JS
Oh yeah, okay yeah
I'll just go ahead and do that
Okay
Yeah
Yeah, sure
Wait, what happened
Oh, I think we're
I think we're typing at the same time
Sorry
That should work, but okay
Yeah, that should work now
Yeah, and it's inferring, cool
Alright
And this is a nice little function
So this is just searching
I guess I'm looking
at the split here
So it's looking at each word
Okay, some of the words start
with a keyword, nice
Yeah, it's not super efficient
like it has some nested loops
but you know
not just some, it has like three levels of nested loops
so it's actually pretty slow
but it's fast enough for us
Exactly, yeah, that's what I'm thinking
Yeah, and does
this handle the empty state
where it's like show all of them unless
you've started typing something
Yeah, yeah, I think it does
You know, it's
Yeah, you can just pass the
I'll go ahead and just do this
Albums, search
Nice
And what now
Well, there's no input
Yep
Yeah, I've
heard on input it's a little more reliable
and it's what I use
No, no
Is that the wrong one
All right
Never mind
It's just a weird name in Quark
It corresponds to on input in the browser
Oh, it does?
Okay, that's what I knew
Oh, that's weird, all right
The more you know
So that's gonna be that, yeah
This should all work
So the last thing to do is just put it on the page
So I'll hop back over here
Let's add suspense again
because it's annoying that
I'm gonna do it because it's annoying
that it waits so much
So
I'll just do
a loading state
because it kind of looks
like something's wrong with the server components
but it's actually just because we don't have suspense
Okay
Interesting, okay
All right, so we have that
and so
we would put the client component in here, right
Yeah
I'm doing
Yeah, you have to do that
We can just do this
Yeah, sure
We'll fix it someday
Someday
Okay, so everything exploded
sadly
That could be on the build tool
That is me
Let me double check on that
The next JS escape patch is looking great
but that is the response
that you'll probably get from the server
because now what we're doing is we didn't filter
which props that our client cares about
Now it's passing down everything
including the song list, which is like
that little uncanny valley I mentioned
If you're not aware, you can
ship a lot of data to the client that you're not expecting
So we could filter it
but right now we're just passing down everything
Yeah, which is what you were
doing anyway in the single page app
Yeah
Can you show what's crashing?
Because I don't see the
Yeah, I'll give it a look
This error doesn't make a lot of sense to me
I just don't see the error
I don't know if
Okay
Does it not show
Yeah, it's crashing in the browser, not the server
Yeah, but I don't see
I think maybe your screen share
doesn't show me the DevTools console
so I have no idea what the error is
Oh, I thought the screen share might actually show it to you
Okay
Interesting
Yeah, it's being really selective
But you're right, it doesn't. It actually hides the DevTools
Alright, let me
And this shouldn't be affecting anyone
at home, this is just our crazy setup
If I do this
now it should work
Maybe
Okay, yeah, now I can actually see it
Yeah, so
Okay, this time it actually doesn't show an error
That's interesting
It just says loading and it never actually resolves
I also made the dev panel
a little too big
Let's see here
Well, yeah, on the key
prompt, but wait, that actually
doesn't make any sense
Oh, I put the key on the list item
instead of on the wrapping div
I can do that, but that shouldn't crash the server
No, that shouldn't crash the server
No, it shouldn't
Yeah, and it's also still
Let me just reboot this
and worst case, I'm assuming
we can copy-paste
Oh, there we go
Okay, something happened in the live reloading
which happens sometimes
Yeah
But we'll just go with it
But yeah, it looks like it's still rendering
on the page, which is good
And we have an input
but since it's tail-ended, it unstyles everything
which is a little too aggressive
Yeah, look at that
So now we have it interactive
searching for artists
and stuff, and I can search by
that as well
Oh, I did the fancy O
Yeah, it's working
Some reason
I don't see your screen updating at all
Oh, really
Yeah, it's stuck
Well, I try
I'm learning this setup as I go
Maybe let's go back to
the thing you shared before
because that definitely was updating
Alright, let's do that again
If I do Chromium tab
You'll have to just read the errors
Just narrate the error
Yeah
Now I'm trying to find which tab it is
I have too many tabs
Oh, I called it future of React
which makes me forget
Okay
Can you see that?
Yeah, now I see it
But it's really slow updates
It's really slow
But it does work
Do you mean it's slow
in the browser, or do you mean the stream is slow?
Definitely on your end
On the browser, it's immediate
as we've mentioned before
Okay
So maybe one thing that would be
interesting to show here is
maybe like
What happens if you remove useClient?
What does useClient actually do?
Maybe we could talk a little bit about this
Yeah, well I'll confess
when you remove useClient
React complains that useState doesn't exist
and that's just a separate thing
with bundlers
Yeah, so it's
I mean, ideally
Oh, okay
It's actually pretty readable now
So it's supposed to tell you that
it's not
like useClient is not supported on the server
Yep, that's what I'm saying
Yeah, so it's
and like the way you would
I think the mental model
you would have, I don't know
Can I draw in your Excalidraw link that you sent to me?
Like would people see it?
Sure
Yeah, I can pull it up right here
Okay, so let me
let me try to open it
One sec
I just need to find the link
But I kind of just wanted to show
what exactly
Okay, so I'll draw
just below your diagram
So let's see, can you see
I drew a
I'm supposed to have
drawn like a rectangle just
below your thing
I think I need to click on the link myself
because if I just go to
Excalidraw.com, it doesn't show it
Yeah, yeah, you need to go to the same link
Go to the DM
with that
Excalidraw
Alright
I think we're here now
Yeah, there we go
Okay, cool
So if we kind of think about
our structure
right now, it's like we have
the server root
and we have
So this is the
well, okay, so this is the
module structure, right?
Well, okay, first I'll draw
the component structure. So we have the server root
that renders
albums
that
itself renders
this searchable
album list
So this is
this is the component structure, but then if we
if we look at the, maybe I'll use
like different
maybe I'll use like a different
different style
So if we look at the file structure
what we see is like there's
the thing you call root.server.jsx
it doesn't have to be named that way
that's what you mentioned
could have just been named like app
or something, and so it imports
the
searchable album
album list.js
and so
the
the way to think about it is like
by default we start with
everything executing
so like
by default everything starts
and like importing starts
on the server, right? So like if you imagine like
this is the server entry point
it means that each import
will be followed, you know, like
like you would expect, and like
all of this stuff would be on the
like in the server
when I say server, I mean
React server, so like RSC
React server components, I don't mean
it doesn't, it's not about like being on
the server in terms of location
again, right? Like it's just the concept
so by default all of these imports
become
part of the code that executes
you know, as part of your server response
and then like if we
if we try to
if you try to use state here
it doesn't really make sense because
this thing
runs only on the server
and so it's never actually
going to be able to have event handlers
or state because this code
just never exists on the client
at all, so it can't react to
user input anyhow
and so when you say use client
and for some reason undo
doesn't work so
I have to, wait seriously
oh really? I can undo
yeah, I can
undo this for some reason
so when we do
so I'll add use client again to
searchable
album list
so if I add use client there, that fixes it
because that redraws the
boundaries, like when you say
use client, you're essentially saying
like
cut this off, you're saying
this
anything from here, this could
import other components, this could
import something else
and so on, but you're saying
anything that imports
searchable list, this thing
actually doesn't exist
this should be on the client
and it's going to client all the way down
which doesn't mean that
it doesn't mean that the
it doesn't mean
all components, so we're talking about
files, we're not talking
we're talking about imports, not about components
you can still have components
that are
server
components inside client components
I'll get to that in a moment
but what I just want to show is like
you kind of
sorry, I just can't
delete anything
like I have to
there we go
by adding use client
you kind of just like
limited the server part to
this
and then the rest is what
your bundler will be
will know to like, oh this needs
anything from here has to go into the client
bundle, and so the server
environment would not even see this
so from the server environment
perspective, the searchable
album list component
it doesn't even know what's in there
it doesn't try to render it, it doesn't try
to do anything with it, it's just completely
opaque, and then on the client
from the client perspective
like when you're actually
on the client, it's really
this part, it's like
it doesn't exist, because
it's already executed, so
the client is only aware of
the output of this thing
it's aware of the output, right
so one of the things that gets
a bit, you know, that always trips
people up is like, okay
but does it mean that
if I just need
one, you know, component
with state somewhere close
to the top, then
you know, it can't
it can't contain
any server components, right
and we can
actually, they have like another
data point that
we can fetch from, just to kind of
illustrate this idea
so you have getById
maybe I can use that, do you mind
if I write a bit of code?
oh yeah, please
yeah, so I just want to illustrate
maybe let's go back to the app
can we make sure the app is working
so that, you know, it's not completely
forked
it's a good thing to check
yeah, is this
the screen share you're able to see?
yeah, yeah
but I see it like as empty
so I don't know if it needs to be restarted
or something
oh no, we just need to
well actually, this is on me
I only detect double quotes
yeah, compilers
alright, that works
oh, okay
yeah, so maybe we can show
the problem you might run
into is
so let's go back
to
for example, index
oh, you have a
can I use this Pokemon example?
you have this Pokemon example in another file
also Primogen, oh my god
thank you for the raid
we have a lot of people pouring in here
right now, thank y'all so much
thanks for stopping by
that is awesome, you're awesome
we're live with Dan
playing with React server components
and learning a ton of things along the way
and right now we are playing
with loading things
asynchronously, seeing the server client
boundaries, and I guess
in a minute, trying to render some Pokemon on the page
if you want to go ahead and try that
yeah, so
let's maybe import
oh, you already imported Pokemon
so that's great
so maybe let's first just
render the Pokemon
above
above the
code is so
I just can't get used to
VS Code, but I'm just trying to
render the Pokemon above the
what is it, the album list
actually
I'm gonna pull it
yeah, okay, yeah
I'm gonna pull it out of the suspense
because the suspense is super slow
because we
let's maybe reduce the delay
I'll set the delay to something that's
oh, we changed
the delay back to be really short
yeah, that should be short now
yeah, okay, so we have a
if we go to root.server.js
you see there's like, we're rendering
Pokemon, and we're also rendering
this album list
and so, suppose that we
for some reason we wanted, like Pokemon
is a server component, right, if you go there
you see it has async await
that's currently
only supported on the server
so, but imagine that in our
app we want to
render the Pokemon from a client
component, right, like let's say we want
to render it between the
search bar and the list of
items
so, if you just try to do it
kind of naively, it won't work
so if I go to
to the
searchable album list, and I'm gonna add
an import for Pokemon
I'm gonna delete the
I'm gonna delete
the Pokemon from
root.server.js
completely, so I will
get rid of it here
and I will add it to our client
searchable album list component
between the input
and the
and the list
and so if you run it now
I think it should crash
like, what does it tell you if you
if you try to run it now
I'm so curious why, but it didn't crash
and it actually ran
that should not work
hang on, what's going on
here
yeah, it's working
wait a minute
but is it between
can you tell the input so that we can actually see the input
because I don't see the input at all
absolutely
yeah, it's right there, it's adding a focus
ring to that
let me add border
solid
okay
yeah, maybe it's not
I guess it's because it's using fetch
so maybe we already
support it on the client as well
so ideally it would be something
that would not be supported
on the client, like a database call
or something like this
right
maybe we can read something from a file
to make this more
make it more obvious
sure, yeah, let's read something from the
file so that we know definitely that
yeah, can we do like
okay, instead of
pokemon, we're gonna do
fs, let's see
I haven't used
can you write some
yeah, I can throw that down, I've only been writing fs calls
for the past however long
yeah, can you do like
readdir, like a list of files
for example, in your
yeah, fs
promises, readfile
maybe readdir
to kind of see the list of
files in the directory or something like this
yeah
or I guess, yeah
that's a thought too, yeah, I can read anything
okay, yeah, whatever
yeah, this isn't
the best thing, maybe if I
tried to read from the db
that would make more sense
sure, there's a thing you could do
db, data
data
at slug there, which is a real
slug
yep
and that, yeah
and then you want to do that
return
you know, a dump
a dump of information
sure
what's that
awesome
yes, maybe let's
see what happens if we try
to do this
or it's already stringified, silly me
alright, so we do that
and then it says, can't resolve node fs
that does make sense
yeah, it's built into node, are you trying to bundle for node
this is an esbuild specific thing
but this is what you would run into with the bundler
where it tries to bundle
this into the client
and it decides, well, you can't import
from node on the client, so I'm gonna
fail out
right, and so the way
and then the way you fix it
the way you kind of do this thing
where, you know, the
I'll switch back to Excalibur
can I see the Excalibur
yep
okay, so, yeah, so the problem we have
right now is like, we're doing this
and, again, this thing
is, this
is rendering, like, Pokemon
which is not actually Pokemon
it's a York album, but let's say it's Pokemon
and then this thing is actually
like, it can only
work on the server
right, so because it uses, like, node
or something, so it actually, like, this
is why it errors
and so the way
you would fix it is
you can
but, and, like, you're
the component structure that you want to have
looks like
this, so
this is what you're trying to do
but the problem is, like
this is a client component
and so you can't import the server component
from client component
but what you can do is
keep the component structure
kind of
the same
except you render
there's not a great way to show it
but they kind of
render it
let me try to
make this a bit nicer
I don't know why this didn't work
let me just show it in code
and then I'll try to redraw the picture
so in code what you do
is you
so you go back
to here, so
we go back to searchable
album list, we can't render
Pokemon here because it's a server component
so what we're going to do instead
we're going to make a hole in our component
so we're going to accept children as a prop
from above
so now we
it's just like, you know, it's the same way
it's not server component specific thing
it's just how you make a hole in the component
that the parent can fill in
and so we copy and paste
Pokemon again, we
go back to our server component
we paste Pokemon import here
and so we
this is not necessary
and so what we do is this
we pass Pokemon as a child
to searchable album list
and so
yeah
and so I think this should work
if you, I don't know, can you try it
yeah
let's give it a try
and also just for my own
sanity, I just want to rename
the component
if anyone's popping in, because apparently there's
2,000 people
if that's true
hello, and thank you
so much
let's pass that in
so this is a file system call
that we're passing down as a prop basically
in order to slot it into our page
so I'll go ahead and do that
and hopefully that's
everything working
so we head over here
we should see that
and then, oh no, things have happened
okay, that's
it's just trying to fetch a file that it can't find
yeah, that's just me
getting file paths wrong
I'll head over here
and because it gets built to a dist folder
it's actually different, that's the issue
there we go
alright, so now we actually get
the readout from the file system
passed down
the server component output
so the thing that
in our case is just
it's reading from a file, but
it's kind of stuffed into
between the parts
the client parts
and the way we can maybe
like the way
let me try to update my diagram
so in
this example
if I'm using blue
for
so we've moved
you see the way we import things
has changed, right, so the component
tree is still the same
like the pokemon is kind of rendered
inside of searchable album list
but the way the imports
are structured is that actually
root.server.js
imports searchable
album list and it also
imports pokemon.js
sorry
it's not pokemon anymore
it's searchable
so yeah, I'm going to change that here as well
and so it
it imports this file as well
and the use client
is only
let me take this
so now use client works because
I think I can just change this
to like blue, right?
sorry, I forgot about
the
so it's kind of
like an island, yeah, sort of
like anything imports will also
be like in the client bundle
but then the remaining stuff like
that
still executes
on the server only and so that's
why it works
yeah, exactly
and I mean you're using all the terms
that we've used at Astro
I was kind of freaking out a little bit when you said
donut islands on a stream the other day
I was like that's what we call them
where what you're doing is
you've created this
an island of client-side
logic and you
want to pass something through a hole
in the middle as a prop
where really anything can be
a prop that's passed down, it can be
data or it can be JSX
and in this case that's what
React is doing, like Bjork album has
become
a prop that is going to
render this stuff out on the server
get that data and then
pass it into the client
so that's another thing about fetching too
what's going to happen is it's going to fetch all the albums
in this setup right now
then it's going to fetch the Bjork album
with the file system call
and once both of those are resolved
it'll pass this guy down
do I have that right?
not quite, so in this example
I think if we
specifically talk about the ordering
I believe it will
try the
oh yeah
because await is
above it
so it's going to fetch the list of
albums and then it's going to
get here, it's going to render the Bjork
album and then it's going to tell
the client, hey here's
the thing you should slot into
the donut and here are
other, because children
is just another prop
there is actually no specific
it could have been called
donut content
equals this
right, and then you would
you would also
because it's just a prop that you pass
and then with
server components, when it
meets a client component
with a bunch of props
it tries to serialize those
props into JSON
and when it meets more JSX
it's like, oh I guess I have more server things to do
so that's why it kind of steps into
the Bjork album and tries to resolve that
and that becomes part of the stream
so that's how it works
very cool stuff
and yeah I was
hoping these devlogs would kind of show you
that but I think these headers are
completely wrong, the important part here
is like, well what's
coming down the wire on this part
and I hope you can still see it, there we go
maybe we can make
the, I think it's just confusing that
it's such a long output
let's just slice
the first 10 letters
or something like this, is that
how you, no I think
0, 10, maybe something like this
oh yeah we can do that too
so maybe let's look for
let's have a look at what's happening
in the dev panel
maybe also let's show just
one first album
so that we
don't have so much to read so I'm gonna make
it like albums, album
0, so I've dated
that you only see one
nice, okay
and let's now have a look at what's actually
happening in the
response from the beginning
yeah
so I mean what I'm seeing
is it starts from showing
you welcome to server components
then we show our loading spinner and we're gonna
wait for the next chunk to come down to replace
that loading spinner
and that's actually here
interestingly, so the 4 and the
3 are a little out of order with what it
decided, it can always
change, but the client part
is just gonna be an import
so this is gonna go import that
file and we don't care what it does
we're just gonna import it and assume it's browser
ready javascript that we can throw on there
and the
information is gonna be there
maybe the way I would describe
it is, if you scroll back
up a little bit
in the
response, notice that
in the protocol we have
for example like h1 or
there's like names of
the tags, right, so we
kind of say, this is a react element
this is a part of the react tree that's like
h1, but then
if we also want to be able to
say, here's
a react component
you need to download
from a script tag
and render, and so if you look a little
bit below
where it says later response
instead of h1, you see
this $l4
which is again implementation detail, it doesn't
actually matter, but this is
a reference to the
previous thing in the response
so instead of h1, you're rendering
searchable album list
so this instruction tells react, here's
where to download this code, it exists
in this script tag
so this is what I meant
by automatic code splitting
because if we remove
searchable, like if we edit our
server with
component for example
to check your
privileges and be like, if you're not an admin
don't show searchable
album list, then
the server will not send the instruction
to download searchable album list
so you wouldn't even have it, you know, you wouldn't
load that bundle at all
because it's just not necessary
so this is what I mean by automatic code splitting
but yeah, other
than that, it kind of says
the later part of the tree is
this module called searchable album list
that exists in your bundle
in your example, it seems like
it's like a separate file
like in optimized bundler
you would have them split into chunks
that have more than
one component of course in them, otherwise
you'd be downloading too many script tags
but yeah, you can see
it says render this thing
that's like a client component
and here are its
props, and so you see album's prop
contains the
album stuff
and then if you scroll down
it says children L5
which is like
reference to some content chunk
that arrives later
It's actually the Bjork album, but we
chopped off very few characters
Yeah, yeah
I might bump that to like 50 or something
and then it'll show you just a little bit
it actually shows you a lot more, doesn't it?
Oh yeah, right here, so this is the later later
chunk once that is resolved
and that gets
passed in as a prop
it gets harder to trace the more components you have obviously
which makes sense
because this is just a dump of what it's actually sending down
but I see what you mean
like oh, it would be right here
so the children of this
component are going to be 5
whenever it resolves, and then here it is
here is that dump
from the Bjork album file
and we're going to pass it into this component
which I think we can trace back up
to
somewhere
5 is
right at the end
5 is children L5
Yep, and that's being
passed into searchable album list
so the numbers correspond
where it's like that's the data
that's the children prop that we're going to pass in
and all of this corresponds to number 4
which is
the actual album list that we're rendering
onto the page
and all of this is
composable, so of course if you put
suspense
around the Bjork album
now, so you do
like, I don't know
let me try to
do something here
I'm also forcing
Dan Abramov to use VS Code, I'm sorry
people, are you a Vim user?
No, no, I can't
but I'm a happy
Sublime user, I don't understand why it keeps
trying to close my tags, like it never
does it the way that I want
Yeah, it's a Prime Machine raid
so I have to ask about Vim, so
it's neither, you use Sublime tags, interesting
So I'm also
going to add an artificial delay
here so that we
can, let's say, wait for
wait for like 2 seconds
like imagine this file system
call is super expensive
so maybe let's have a look at what
happens after this
Yeah, let's see what happens
Okay, something
failed with just parsing
the file
Don't know what happened there, let me double check
It might have tried to save at the wrong time
I know VS Code can get out of sync with that
Yeah, there we go
Okay, and yeah, now we have this out of order
streaming setup
where when you load the page first
it loads everything
then it does the file system call and it slots
it in here later
while preserving the other markup
that you have
Yeah, and so the cool
about it from my perspective is
like in
you know, we parse some
server stuff that still might be
waiting for something, but we kind of
unblock the rest of the
even like client stuff from rendering by
just putting suspense in there
Yeah, exactly
It's the easiest switch to slot into
where the default is like wait for everything
which is usually what you want so you don't
have layout shift, and then it's like
well actually I do have
I actually have a way to handle layout shift
I have like a loading spinner that's a perfectly sized
skeleton, so I'm going to see
Yeah, here it's not really ideal
what we're doing where it like bops things
down the page as soon as it comes in
because you know, if that's like above the
fold on your hero banner
you probably want to have like a loading state
that's matched up to it
Yeah
So I don't know how much
time to have
but how deep do we want to go
because it would be fun to also
like I added a bunch of hacks just to
kind of show the idea
but I think it might be fun to
get rid of the weird
PR problem component and instead look at
what it would look like to
refetch, like to do
search on the server, I think that's like one
That would be very cool
Yeah, I mean I only
booked two hours to like be conscious of your time
but if you're good to keep going, I am
as well
I think I have some more time
I don't have to run anywhere
Okay
So to do that, I'm wondering if
we can, should we hop over
to the Next.js example to try server search
or are we still comfortable here?
I think we can try to do it here
like if it doesn't work, we can do
you know, we can use Next.js but now I'm kind of like
you seem to have a setup that kind of
works and I like the
you know, I like your
I like your, it's
no small effort because like none of it is documented
so it's
yeah, it is
impressive, so I'd say
let's keep going until your setup breaks
I like it, it's gotten
close, it's definitely gotten close
but the duct tape's holding
Yeah, I really like your development panel
I think I'm a bit conflicted
about it because I'm worried
that like people on the stream would be like
oh, this is so complicated, like
this whole output, but it's really
kind of like reading the network tab
so the point is not, you know
you wouldn't see this as a user
but I do see the value, you know, as an
instructional tool of here's how it actually
works, because it's not that
complicated if you think, you know
about what it's
trying to do
Yeah, exactly. Yeah, the dev panel
was really, I just intended it for
like the first 30 minutes to show
oh, here's the data streaming down and now
it waits for suspense, but it's like
it's also kind of useful to see like how much
stuff is coming down, like when we
pass down albums as a prop
suddenly the response got huge
because now it's passing down like all the songs
and stuff that you don't care about, so
it's useful to just see like volume and time
not necessarily the details
so maybe just like showing
well, it's always dangerous to show kilobyte
numbers because they're lies, but there's probably
a way to do it
Yeah, I'd love to see them both
so let's
let me just clean up, I want to
get rid of this part that doesn't
make sense because we just added it
as a demo, so let me
clean it back up to what
we had that
still made sense
as an example, I'm gonna get
rid of this children prop as well
Yeah, so I think
we should be back to our previous
example
and instant
search
and yeah, do you want to
do you want to try to add the
like the add in the
so what do we want
to do, right? Like we want to
we want to refetch
the server component tree
when you type into the input
right? Right
so maybe we want to
do like search on the server
maybe we show like just the first
like, I don't
know, two results
it doesn't seem to have like much data here
anyway, right? But maybe we
Yeah, there's only three albums
Okay, yeah
Yeah, so do you want to
do you want to drive
edit and we'll see
where it becomes confusing
I can try to do that
and one thing before we go
I'm actually going to
make the dev panel just a little bit
less tall in case
we have issues with that
I, oh man, I thought it would be an easy switch
where did I put it
yeah, okay
yeah, alright
and it scrolls for the rest, perfect
so in order to
do something like that
well the first thing
I'm going to do, I guess
and this feels like a coding interview right now
I'm thinking, but
yeah, we can remove that
we're not going to use that anymore
no use state
the filter album function is fine
to keep around
and as you input things
I assume we're going to
well, if we put query parameters
on the top of the page, it's going to refresh the
browser on every
input, but if we did like
JSON requests, then we could avoid
refreshing the page every time
I don't know, there's two ways to do it
so I think
the, maybe you're kind of
approaching it from the perspective of like
how would I do this in a client-side application
so you're like
yeah, well I'm thinking form requests, I guess
like literally just using form action
and submitting it and using stuff
but I assume you have
something else in mind that isn't just a form action
yeah, so if form action
is usually used for stuff
like post, I guess
here we kind of just want to refresh
the output
so I think I would probably use get
but also form action
yes, like default browser
handling of forms, like that would reload
the page completely
so it makes sense that that's not
quite what we want
I think the
so let me maybe think a little bit
about this as well
so I think we still need
I think we still need
state, actually, because we want
the
well, not
okay
okay, so there's a question
of like how deep
do we want, because this is the stuff that
Next.js or an RSE
framework is supposed to handle
so I think there's kind of two
levels to this, like we can
do this with
like do we want to hook it up to the URL
because one option is to
hook it up to the URL
and other options like not to
I think
probably not hooking it up to the URL
might be a bit less code
so maybe we
sure, yeah
maybe that's
maybe that's what
yeah, because I guess what I'm wondering
is, because what we're trying to avoid is
passing the whole album list as
a prop and doing the filter logic on
the client, so I assume
that would also mean if we're not passing down the
prop, where
if we're doing anything client-side, it's just
going to be the search box, but not the
Yeah, exactly, yeah, so maybe let's
do you want to like rearrange
the code a little bit, like I think I would
just move the
yeah, so maybe we do like
the search box component
and we make that a client component
and then we extract it to like a new
file and then we keep this file
as it is
Yeah, let's go ahead and do that
I'll make a search over here
and pull that out
and also, I'm actually just going to
undo my way back here
I won't save that because I think that
breaks everything
Okay, I'm in the search now
and in here, I will
do input
Oh, it doesn't know about state yet
so let me introduce that
This is so much fun, I'm really enjoying it
Oh, it remembered my styles
It remembered my styles
Oh, that's so good
Okay
I don't even understand, like, you're
using Copilot or something
because I've never used it, I don't even know how
what it is
So, I think Copilot
and actually the Prime Engine had a good
video on this, where like for
migrations, it's really good
at knowing context, of like
it knows I typed a search box before
and now it's picking up like, oh, you're probably
extracting this to a separate component
Let me pull in those styles that you wrote earlier
So does it like
stuff it into the prompt? Like, how
does it keep track of the context?
Well, it understands
your code base, as far as I know
and it is
I don't know how much of it is local
versus network requests
but, yeah
We should have a dev panel to see
what it sends and what it receives
That would be nice to know
because like, yeah
if it's sending your code base over to
Wired, that is a massive problem
I don't know what it
does. That's the scary part
I don't know what it says
It's fine. Yeah, so let's
Okay, let's go. Let's get this working
Yep
And everyone is searching for what my
theme and font are. Just calm down
I'll make extensions someday, people
But I use Monolisa font and the
Houston theme, made by Astro
and by using it, you get access
to this beautiful little Houston floating guy
in your editor, anytime you want it
So, you know, go ahead and use that
Dan, you actually can't see that, sadly
No, no, I see the default theme
Yeah, dang
Yeah, we have this little
Houston animation
where it's just a Houston panel, if you want to
just have him watch what you're doing
and he gets progressively more sad
the more syntax errors you have
Okay. Yeah, I have no idea
what you're talking about, but
Don't worry about it
I can send a screenshot later
Okay, okay
But yeah, we have our search box here
and
well, we can render
that inside of our root server, I guess
We can hop all the way back
Well, why though?
Can't we just render it in
the component
you extracted it from?
That's a good point
You already have it here
And I guess our filter code
is going to go over there, too
No, I mean, I don't think you have
to change anything
Oh wait, no, it doesn't go over there, that's the whole point
Yeah, yeah
Here is where it goes in
Yeah
Yeah, so the problem
right now is that you don't really have
Yeah, you don't really have filtered albums
yet, but we'll add it back
later
So I think for
I would write it like this
And then the thing you want to
render is this
Let's just verify that it still works
Yeah, it is working
But then typing into the input
doesn't really do anything, right?
Right
So I think maybe
again, there's two ways we could go
about this, either
with the URL or
without
I think with the URL probably makes
more sense, because if we're
going
to show what frameworks do, we might as well
just try to do it
ourselves
So maybe let's make it so that when you type
into the input
let's make the URL update
using client-side
like history.pushState
We could use the history package
I think it's a bit more
But we could probably just use the browser API as well
Let's start with the browser API and then see
if we need anything more
But let's try to make it so that when you type
into the input, we also update
the URL
Gotcha
Yeah, for something like that
On
change, sure
Basically that
But then we want to also
I have to think about this
So is it window.location
pushState
It's been a while since I've used this API
I think it's history.pushState
Yeah, I think it is
history.
Yep, yep, yep
pushState
I think
So there's like pushState and a replaceState
I don't know if the search bar
is like
Yeah, that will
We don't want history
as we type
So maybe let's check
if this works
I don't actually see your address bar
so I don't know if it works, you'll have to tell me
It's really tiny at the top
but it's up there
When you bump the font size
it doesn't bump the size of that, sadly
I don't see it because
it doesn't share
Oh, it doesn't
That's so silly
Well, it is working
I can tell you that much
It is working
Just putting up search equals
Okay, I'll have to believe you on this
So
Okay, so maybe let's
I think I might
have to drive this a little bit
if you don't mind
I will need your help
as well, I think, because I
can only do the parts that I know about
So I'm gonna
go to the thing
called root.client.js
and it's kind of interesting
You do have
kind of the server entry point and the client
entry point
and it's a bit confusing because conceptually
it's the server entry point that's
the real root of your app
It's the real root
where things start conceptually
but then
in reality, you do need this bootstrapping
thing that makes
this real root appear somewhere on the page
Yeah, what I really want to call it is
bootstrapping and index
Yeah
I think that's what it is
It's also kind of like, if you think about
how would it work with nested routing
you would also
have the server
be the root
It would also be possible to start
from the middle of
some nested route and treat that
as a root, and that's what happens with
navigations in NextAppRouter
and then this thing
that you have here, this bootstrapping
thing, that would turn
into the client-side
routing part
that bootstraps
the top-level thing, but also
bootstraps these holes
and manages
how to slot in the server responses
into them
This is hidden in a framework, that's what
Next.js does, for example
but we're going to do a simple
version of that where it only bootstraps
them at the top, but I'm just saying
if you were building a nested router
you would have to
have a very similar thing
managing it somewhere
around your
route holes
to replace them
if necessary
But yeah, so
you have this thing where here
so these are internal APIs
this file is the
kind of stuff that, as a product developer, you
wouldn't touch or do any of
that, and I also
want to make clear that
all of this stuff below is
for debugging, because it's
your dev panel component
so it actually has nothing to do with React
but then
as a framework developer
this part is kind of the bootstrap
where you're like
okay, here's where
I'm going to move this here because it's unrelated
Yep
Like
Honestly, all of this is unrelated
This was me trying to
I never finished it
Wait, show me
what did you delete?
Yeah, this was some code I was writing
to allow multiple routes
and all it was really doing is getting
the current window location and fetching the
file that corresponds to that location
Okay, yeah, no, we don't need
that, but we are going to need something
similar, but let's
delete this for now, it's fine, let's delete this
So what I'm going to do is
what it currently does
I don't love this, can I just rename this
to slash
Yeah
I'll see what source code needs to be fixed to make that work
but yeah, that's what it is
I think it's in the
handler, right?
Yeah, I think it might just be this
So maybe let's change this
to rsc, let's verify that it
still loads
I mean, obviously it doesn't have to be called that way
I just kind of want to stress that
Okay, yeah, so there's just one
endpoint, it's not like multiple files
or anything, it's just one endpoint
And so I'm going to make a react
component that's like
I don't know, I'm going to call it
like boots
I don't know, client
root or something like this
which is just this bootstrapping
thing
And currently
Yeah, I'm going to move
I'm going to move this a little bit, so I'll make it
render restrict
mode, and I'm just going to do this
client root thing here
Okay
Our
component
And then I'm going to
So again, this
is like create from fetch
This is like an internal API
for framework developers
This is the protocol reader
So we have a protocol writer
that runs on the server, so if you go
to
the
Yeah, so if you
go to the handler, this is where
you wrote this logic
for the actual handler
of this endpoint that runs
server components, you'll see
you have
So you call this react-server-dom
which is maybe a bit
confusing because people might think it's
like react-dom-server
I didn't know what to call it
Yeah, I don't know either
React-server-dom-webpack
And I thought, is that really what it is?
But that's the package
I don't think we actually figured out
how to name this thing
This is not
SSR, this is not
the react-dom-server
that emits HTML
This is the thing that emits
This is the protocol writer
This is the thing that executes
your server components
and emits this protocol
this streaming thing that you show
in the dev panel
And so the
it comes from this package
I don't actually think you need
that browser here, I think this should just work
Can you check if that
Oh, I guess I broke some other
I think it'll try to import
the node version, and that uses
pipes, and I was like, I think I can do it simpler
So I did it this way
Okay, cool
Alright, and then
Yeah, if I go to the correspondent
this is the reader
This is the thing that
reads the client protocol
and really, all it does
is it turns it into
JSX, essentially
So it converts the
it streams the output
from the server, and it converts it
to a tree of
lazy components that get
filled in later
And this is why
it's kind of funny, React
the React library
doesn't really have any code to support
server components
because it's
like, this ability to
render a tree from the server
it relies on exactly the same
mechanism that, for example, React.lazy
uses, which is just
this built-in support in React
to have a tree where some parts
are not ready, and then suspense will catch
them, and so this is the thing that
translates from the protocol
to a lazy React tree, and then
React knows how to deal with lazy trees
And so the
we could maybe
call this stream
create from fetch, and then you have
fetch from this
RSC endpoint, I think that's how it
worked, and
I guess we can just say this is
just JSX
maybe, well, lazy JSX
I don't know. Yeah, lazy JSX
Yeah, the best
way is like, that's the interpreter
that's going to take these instructions and
turn them into JSX, and that
is actually what we get
Yeah, so maybe let's see if
this works so far, because I'm going to
add a few things
Okay, can I
refresh it?
Yeah, it's working
Awesome, and so the thing that we want
to be able to do now is
before we deal with client-side
navigations and stuff, I think
what we want to do is just
to be able to pass
something during the initial load to the
server, right? That's the easiest part
It's like, if you have some
query in the query string and you
refresh the page, at least we should be
able to ask the server to
filter for that
It's like with manual refreshes for now
and then we'll fix that
So I think what we want to do is
we can look at
I don't actually remember
how to do it, but
Okay, so here's what I want
I want to
search equals
Okay, so
let's actually start there
I want to search for
what is it?
Yeah, let's say
fame, that's what I'm searching for
This is my search query
So I'm going to look for the album
of fame
And then I will go to
the server handler
So now we need to plumb that information
into your root server
component so that it knows
what the search
parameter is
And so I'll go to the
your server
handler. Again, this is the framework
part, like a framework
Yeah
And they have path name
So that we pass the query
Like we pass
all the query arguments as
props to
Yeah, it should be right up here
So it's just a web-friendly URL
So we can just do search params
and grab that
I'm so bad at these APIs
I'm like, I don't remember
I think it should be like has and get
in order to access
what we're looking for
Yeah, it can be turned into
just plain JSONs so that we can
spread it as props to the
Docker component
I think there's a way to do it
if you do like
Ah, there's a simple way
and I can't remember what it is
search params
JSON
equals, yes! That's it
Yeah, you convert it to an object
and then JSON stringify it, thanks
Well, okay, then you would have to parse it again
But
Hang on
No, just this
Yeah, just this
Okay, is that
Okay, we'll see
Let's see if it works
So now we want to
Yeah, and now we want to
This is your app here
This is the rooted-server.js expert
So this is your
It's actually
Oh, okay, you're calling it
I think that's a bit wrong
I mean, it ends up working
Yeah, I couldn't get it working without calling it
I don't know why
Like, I think this is supposed to work
So I think you're supposed to
I mean, you're like server root
That's how you call it, right?
That's just the expert of this thing
And I think you're supposed to be
Can I use just the expert?
Yeah, no
I don't know how to process on this thing
You could use react-create-element, right?
Yeah, yeah, that's what I'm going to do
So I'm going to do like
convert createElement
from react
And I'm going to do
createElement for server root
And I'm going to parse it
Well, I'm just going to parse
the search
params object as props
And then in the server root
I'm going to try to
read the
What did I call it?
I call it search
Which has nothing to do with search API
It's just like our variable name
And I'll say
we are
the bytes of keeping certain things
in the wrong place
I'm looking for search
So let's see if that works
Try to load it with like
search
Construct your search of undefined
Okay, so the props aren't being passed
but I think we have to restart
Because it's not going to
Okay!
Oh my god! It's working
Okay, nice, nice
Whoa! Oh, that's cool
Okay, so now your task
is to
I want you to do the
to take search into account
and do the filtering, like add the filtering back in
Mm-hmm
Yeah, that's interesting
Because I would want to do it from here, right?
Because I need to trigger a new
create from fetch
Well, let's not think about this yet
So for now I just want to do it for the first render
So it's not going to respond
to input, but let's just make it
respect the initial URL
Mm, okay
So for now
you just need to plumb down
We got it in the root components
Connect the logic so it actually does the search
on the server
Okay, so we would need
to pass this search down
Yeah
I mean, ideally a framework would make
So the way this works in Next
is they make it available as
import
I don't know, import search
part
I think there's some way to get it without
plumbing it down in Next
Mm-hmm
Maybe I'm confusing it with headers
I can actually check
Yeah, because you can't do hooks
when you're passing down server
contacts, that's still like an unexplored thing
Yeah
Yeah, okay
Page params are props
like they become props to your page
function, so it's
pretty much almost exactly
as Next.js would do it
So yeah
let's keep passing it down
So I do that
and
we've done that
I don't think you passed it to this album component
I think you missed it here
Oh, did I?
Okay
I passed it down to searchable album list
and I passed it to search
Yeah, but you don't pass it to album search
It's undefined
Oh, yeah
That's actually good, Squiggles
Yeah
Squiggles
Yeah, the squiggles are really annoying
There's some kind of thing in TypeScript
where we need a solution
to allow
async await
Right
Okay, and we have it
in our input right here
Okay, but we also want to have it
in the... wait, what did you do?
Let me see what you did
So this should...
Yeah, so that makes sure the input matches
what's actually being passed to the server
and now we can also use it here
which I assume is actually what you're asking for
to start with
So we have filtered albums
and that can just be
filter albums, pass in the search
Yep
Okay
It works
Nice
So it works for the first load
but then it doesn't... like if you type
if you type into the input
Yeah, it's not refetching
It's not refetching
Okay, so I'll try
the refetching piece for a little bit
So I think
for refetching
the way we would do it in the framework
That's my...
Wait, let me open the right file
Okay, so I'm going back to this
I don't actually know, do you see where I am
in VS Code?
How do you know which file I'm in?
Does it show you?
Or which part are you asking about?
Do you know where...
Do you track where I am in VS Code?
Oh yes
No, I can't. I'm in the file
Okay, cool
So what we want to do here
is essentially...
This is the framework bit
But what we want to do here
is we want to
replace this thing with
another stream essentially
and show that JSX tree
instead
So
the way we could do this
is... let me
think a little bit
So
I think
the way we would do it
let me write a little bit of code
So
I think we would hold the...
So we need to create a cache
Yeah, this is what I was trying to build
a little bit ago
where I wanted to call createFromFetch
inside of here
and be able to
store the lazy JSX
in a state variable
and return that result
to re-render
Yeah, yeah
So I think that's kind of what we want to do
and
maybe
maybe we can make
actually like this
ClientRoot, I'm going to call
I'm going to have a component called
a router
that renders ClientRoot
and I think
from the perspective of the ClientRoot
I think I'd like it to receive
the
should it receive the search params
or
I'll just
call it router for now and I'll write
the line in the router and then maybe I'll split
the components
But I think I want to have a
I want to have a cache
so
it's just going to be
just a regular map
So I want to
I think I want to keep a
this
createFromFetch
this represents build the stream
and kind of response you can use later
because it's
as long as we don't create it during rendering
it's going to be showing the same thing
So I think
what we want to do is we want to
I'm going to turn
off the light because it's getting really dark
Oh, okay
So I think we want to keep it
keep
a response cache per
this string
This is going to be the key
of how we're going to
cache it. So I'm going to have a map
Oh, yeah, you're already
jumping ahead to caching there
Yeah
So the initial
version I'm going to do is like
if the cache does
not have anything for
Yeah, so the
router
Okay
Okay, so I'm going to
I would assume
that this is like an effect
that's going to update as the
window updates and we're going to use
that to trigger
I think we're going
to do that, but
we're going to get there
Give me a moment
I wrote this kind of code like a couple
of times, so
I'm still not sure what's the best way to structure it
But I think
maybe I can call this component
server output
That's kind of what it is
And then this
is kind of the URL
I'll use URL as the key
And so I think that is the part
Yeah, and then the router will
return server
output
And I'll just hard code the URL here
So that will be the
kind of the initial URL
And later we'll make it
respond to
the client-side routing
But I think what we want to do
is
I don't need this anymore
Instead, the router
renders this thing and this thing
I guess maybe I call
this server
endpoint
server endpoint
Nah, it's going to be
a cold URL, sorry
So if it's not in the
If the URL is
not in the cache, I think we'll want to
put it
put this
into the cache
Let me see
So this is going to be
URL
And then
I think we just want to return
what's in the cache for this URL
And so
this might be
Yeah, that's interesting
I don't actually use set cache here
Although there is a use case
It's a ref as it stands
That's what it's acting like
Yeah
But I think we do need it for some
Like I think we would need this for invalidation
It's just, in our case, we don't have
Invalidation, so we don't have a reason
to do this
Because it's always, like it's caching everything forever
But if we had
invalidation where we want to say
throw away the cache you had
because something got modified
Then we would model it as
a set state where we
set state to a new map
So it would be like an empty cache
And that's why, like, conceptually
I think it should leave in state
That's why it's not like a ref
And maybe we can actually
also show it
We could have a small example that shows it
Yeah
Also, sorry that
Sorry I just do, can we do a quick pause
for like a bathroom break, get some more water
Yeah, yeah, sure
Okay, cool. I also don't have a standby screen
So, uh, yeah
BRB
Okay, one second
Alright
Am I still on the
stream? Like, I don't know, are people there?
I guess
maybe
Um
Yeah, I don't really have access to the
I don't have access
to the actual server, so I have
I have no idea if this
if this code works
because I can't, for some reason I can't
I can't
Like, the VS Code tunneling
doesn't work for me, I think it's
maybe
because of a firewall
or something
But maybe if, yeah, maybe for now I could
just go over this a little bit
So, yeah, we render
this router that, like, renders
this server output
for this key
and then, this might look a bit
weird, because this might look, you know, like
aren't you supposed, like, aren't components
supposed to be pure, like, isn't this
a mutation? And so
the key thing here is that
it's completely unobservable
So
it's, um
because, like, the state
the state is, like, local to this component
and this lazily
kind of fills it in the first time
you ask for it, it kind of acts
as
you know, it is going to give you, like, the same
result for, like
multiple attempts, regardless of
in, like, which order you do them
and this is why it's okay to
mutate in this particular
example
Yeah, so maybe let's see if this
works at all, like, can we
Did I break it?
I don't know yet
This should, I mean, as it looks
it should be fine
but if we save it, we get
something
Okay
properties of undefined reading to lowercase
Okay, so
Something's trying to render
that shouldn't be
Well, wait, are we currently
do you have question mark
search equals blah blah in your
URL bar? I do
Oh, actually, no, wait, no, we're not using that
we've hardcoded it
Create from
fetch fetch URL
Yeah, it's happening server-side
So
it's trying to, okay
I think it's because the dev panel
assumes that you're fetching the same thing
so if we just stop rendering the
dev panel, I think it'll just go away
Oh, no, that's, wait
let's just fix it, it's fine
I'll fix it
Let's just make it so that
the, so since the URL
is owned by the router, I'm just
I'm just gonna
Yeah, I'm just gonna render dev panel here
myself
So we can
put dev panel
and I'm gonna make this URL
a constant
and
I'm gonna pass it to both
things
so that
I guess I don't actually know how your
dev panel works, let me have a look
So I'm gonna get rid of, oh, you have like
a separate root
It's just a separate root and separate call
I ideally wanted it to trace
what was happening
Oh, I see
And I couldn't find a way to do it, so I just
do another fetch at the same time
and apparently it wasn't, I did two roots
I see, I see
Interesting
Yeah, right
because you're not hooking into the same
stream, but okay, that's fine
so we'll do the same thing
except it would, you know, do it with a different
different URL
because if I just pass the URL here
and I also make it dependency of the
effect
I think it would, well I guess
like our panel would behave maybe a bit
weirdly
if the URL changes
but maybe not, so let's just see if it works
And then can we
where's the HTML for
your thing, so that
Oh yeah, that
should be in a public folder, but I
didn't have time for it, so I think it's inside of this
templates index file
I'll bring it over here
But yeah, it's very simple
This is all it's doing
I can just remove it from here, right
and make it like a regular
Okay, yeah, so I'll just
get rid of this
and then I'll
and so this is not going to be like a separate root
it's just a React component that we're
rendering
Does it have any styles
that are, that depend on that
ID
Uh
I don't think so
Oh, because you're using
Tailwind, there's no styles
Love it, love it
Yep, hacks for everything
That's the amazing thing about
You just copy and paste things
move them around
Works fine
So style files
Okay, so let's see if
Okay, does this work
So if you
try it now
Did we fix it
Yeah, we got no errors
and we just get fetching from server
which I think is right, since we're not
rendering anything yet
But we are, no I think we are
rendering, like we're supposed to be
rendering that JSX tree for that
URL
Oh, okay, that actually should work, huh
So it does fetching from server
Can you see if there are any errors in the console
Yeah, let's see, there's no server errors
The client console, it looks like it's just getting
the first one, but it's not reading the rest of the
stream onto the page
And I remember that earlier
we removed the function
call and changed it to createL
That was working
So this is the part
Okay, maybe let's
go back a little bit
and simplify it
and then see if it still breaks
So I'm gonna make
a fake thing
and I'm gonna
instead of router, I'm gonna render this fake thing
It's a bit hard
for me to debug because I don't see the output
and I don't see
I can't actually check anything
But maybe
let's go back to
like
if I know
my URL
my thing
equals
Sorry
I'm gonna name it in my
weird ways
Yeah, so I'm gonna create from fetch
for my URL
Oops, that's gonna be my
URL
And we're gonna render this
Okay, so can we just get this thing
working? Does it still break?
This works
Okay, this works
And then
if I swap it out with the router
I can confirm that it doesn't
work again
Okay, it doesn't work
So let's switch it back to fake thing
It is trying to resolve the client-side
component import though, which is interesting
But yeah, that's working
Okay, so let's
maybe now change this to just
use this
component to see if the problem is with this
component. Try it again
That is not
working
That is not working, so that's where the problem is
It's the cache
Okay, that's good though because it means
something here
What am I doing wrong?
Okay
Cache, if not cache
has cache set
cache is
a piece of state
If it doesn't have this URL
put this
thing into it and then
read it. Yeah, I don't see
a mistake in the code, but maybe let's
keep, you know, let's keep
I mean, we can log what this is
Yeah, let's log what this is
But I'm not going to see the log because I don't see
the console
It should be the browser console, so I can at least
bump up the font size on the screen share
No, no, your tab share
doesn't show me anything
You're right
Alright, you get chunk pending, which is a familiar
site
Yeah, that seems legit. Okay, no, it's fine
I think I have a way to debug it, like I have
a methodology. I'm just going to
put it piece by piece and then we'll find
where the mistake is
Okay, so the next thing is I'm going to
copy and paste like this
part into the fake
thing
It's also doing an infinite loop, which might
be something
Yeah, that seems
good to know
if not cache, but I don't know
why it... Yeah, because I was getting infinite
logs
Interesting
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah
Very interesting
Yeah, well, let's
keep going. I think I should be able to
figure it out
Okay, just
Okay, so the first thing I could maybe
try is just like
for now, I'll move this cache
outside maybe
So I've had this issue in the past for
when I tried to use use
and I didn't put any
wrappers around it, I didn't
put a cache, and it was calling my
useFetch infinitely
because it was a weighted
promise, and I don't know if that's why
because this is definitely another case of returning a
promise and passing it
Yeah, maybe
that is...
Yeah, maybe actually, maybe you're right. Let me see
Maybe that's not... Let me check
how our
our
fixture does it, because maybe I'm
just supposed to use use, and we
don't have warnings yet, so
that's why
Yeah, okay, let's try this
actually. Maybe that's how it's
supposed to work. So I'll import
use from React
and let's...
instead of fakeThing, let's render the
router again, and let's
get this back, except
this will be just
lazyJSX
and then I'll say return
use lazyJSX
because I think we haven't implemented
support for this yet, but we also haven't
implemented good error messages
Interesting. Let's see if that's better
That's the same
Now it's the same
Yeah, we're still getting nothing
back. Okay, now
let's try this
thing next. Can you
refresh?
Ooh, things are happening
Okay, I don't...
Let me look here. Okay, we do have something on the page
Okay, so this
works. This works
Interesting
So what was the important bit? Wait, what changed?
Well, the part that changed
is the... No longer useState
Okay
Yeah, I don't understand
It definitely works like in
the example I wrote a few days ago
Yeah
Oh, wait, maybe we can remove strictMode
I mean, I wouldn't necessarily...
I couldn't get anything
to work without strictMode
Oh, it works! Okay, nevermind
Okay, if we remove strictMode
and I put this back
Let's see
I think maybe we just have a bug there
Is it still broken?
Yeah
Yeah, maybe it's like a different React
version
Yeah, I'm on an experimental
18 release because it's the only thing that
worked with createFromFetch
But yeah
Okay, let me see
Experiment. Yeah, I don't...
I think...
Let's try to
use a different React version
I will copy and paste the version that
I think should work
Can we
yarn and
whatever
It like upgrade to
a new experimental release?
No, it's actually
different. It's like the next
It's like a canary
Because I don't know what's...
Experimental might have too many things
enabled that could be broken
Could be
That could be the reason
I mean, can't we just roll without the state variable
though? Because I feel like...
I just want to see if that helps
If it doesn't help, we'll just roll without it
It's just annoying because like
I do have this working in literally
I know
It's written the same way in a different project
and I'm like, why doesn't
it work if I have it working in another
file
Yeah, as a framework maintainer, whenever something goes wrong in Astra
I'm like, no, no, no, what is it?
What version is it?
No, I already did
You don't need to specify versions. I already put them in package.json
You could just like re-run this
Perfect
Oh, you just found it
Alright
That'll do
So these are next releases instead of experimental
Yeah
These are a bit more kind of stable
Okay
And yeah, this is where you get funny peer dependency issues
Yeah
And it's the same thing, I think
Interesting
Yeah, so it's
Yeah, it's running infinitely
Can we wrap this
with the actual cache helper
from React?
No, we don't use that anymore
Okay, yeah
Okay
Okay, let's
Okay, let's forget about
I mean, it doesn't matter that much because we're not doing
invalidation anyway, so
let's just, I'll add back the strict mode
and I will
Yeah, I will remove the state variable
I'm not sure why it doesn't work
without it, but maybe we just broke something
So, yeah, I'll just keep it global
But I think at least like this
this is actually supposed to
I don't need use here in that case
I think
So I think this is supposed to work
I know, we definitely need use
What's going on?
Oh, we do? Okay, I can add that
Yeah, objects, okay, it's saying promise
is invalid
Okay, yeah, so we
didn't implement this yet, so let's
Okay, let's put it back
If anyone at home is wondering
like what's going on, we've kind of graduated
from exploring Rack server components
to like how do they really work
within a framework if you're trying
to build one
So this is going more in the weeds for sure
but one interesting fact is like when you want to
unwrap asynchronous stuff
on the client, use is
basically in a wait for the client, right?
But it can also do other things
beyond a wait
Yeah, yeah
Okay, so I think that
actually should be enough for now, I don't think we need
more fancy
So let's just hook up the router
to the actual routing
Right, so let's
Maybe you can drive this bit
What we want to have in the router
we have the URL
variable, so let's make that
initialized to
window.location
Let's take
the search query from
the actual location
and let's make it update
as the location updates
Yeah, so for that
Well, I'm wondering
where it would go
but first I'll just do
window.location.
We want it as a prop yet, let's just do search
Do that
and we want
Oh boy
I don't really want all of that
but
yeah, that's fine
Clean up, I don't know yet
but to do
abort controller
for create fetch
Oh no, you don't need to do this part
We already have this part down below
Like all we want to do is
Yeah, all we want to do is
we want to have
we want to have something that gives us
window.location.search
all the time
Okay, so literally that
Yeah, but
Okay, so we're going to build this in later
because right now it's not going to be reactive
to anything, it's just going to render the initial
cache
Yeah, so I think maybe I can try to do
so what does window.location.search
return, what kind of file
is it like a string or
Yeah, that'll just be the string, so question mark
Yeah, that, so it's a key that we could use
Okay, so we do need
this thing
Do we need to
encode the URI component
or is it already encoded?
Yeah, I think we can put this
in the create from fetch actually
Might make a little more sense, I don't know
But yeah, this would be right
Okay
You could also just do
window.location.pathname if that's what we're looking for
Okay
Or actually no, that's the query we're making
so this is right
Okay, let me just
see, yeah, I think we can just
so we don't need this, I think that's
that's the URL we want
to get, and I think we
I agree, maybe this makes sense to actually
put here, but maybe
let's just do like a
useEffect thing that's going to
be
so I think this, we're going to model
this as like, you know, a state
so this is the
kind of the initial
state, and then
when we have a
so I think it's
window.addEventListener
popState, I think
that's the thing that
Oh yeah
That's the thing that's supposed
to be
to be doing this
And then
this is
where we
I
don't know if
this will
work, but maybe it
does, so let's
can we
see if this works?
That should do it, I think
so
yeah, is this actually
going to log anything?
So this is going to re-render
Oh, yeah, this might actually do
a lot more, so as I
start typing, nothing is changing
Does it
Let's see handlePopState
Well, only I can see it, sadly
But as I, okay, it's not
doing handlePopState
It's not calling it? Maybe I
miss, is that wrong?
Because I think you
were calling the replaceState, right?
I think you're right
windowPopState
I don't think it's going to
fire
navigateSessionHistory, right
It changes the currentHistory
entry to that of the last page
of the, right, so it might
require pushState instead of
replaceState in order for it to work
No, that
doesn't sound plausible
to me
I think
replaceState should trigger
the browser
I would think so
Is this
Okay, maybe
Sorry, I'm just going to debug this
locally in, like, Chrome
I don't see anything that's happening
It's very hard to do anything
if I don't have the console
I can do one last try
on just sharing the browser window
instead and see if it actually
Yeah, let's try sharing the browser window
Yeah
I can do that
shareScreen
window
There
All right, and I'm going to start typing
It is working, I think
Oh, but then it stopped
Okay, no, I see
typing, okay, so
Does it understand correctly that
handled never runs?
Yeah, handledPopState
Yeah, handledPopState's never running
HandledPopState is not
But we do have
We do have it
That's so weird
Let me just try this
Let me try this locally
I'll just try to do
window.addEventListener
popState
with some
log
Sure
listener, and then I'm going to try to
window.history.replaceState
with some
Oh, yeah, that doesn't
run it for some reason for me either
Let me try pushState
Maybe you were right
No, pushState doesn't do this either
handledPopState
Does anyone, can you ask somebody
who knows how
browsers work?
Why is this not doing anything?
Yeah, I'm sure there's a lot of people in chat
who know how browsers work
I can also
Well
There's people I can message
Because like the
mdn, I'm looking at the mdn examples
It's right here
They show the exact same thing
Right?
What is different in what we're doing?
Oh
Oh, interesting
Yeah, notice that the pushStates don't
do it, but back and go will
log
Oh
I forgot that's how it works
This is so confusing
Because this API was invented
before client-side routing
Yeah, so there's a new
transitions API, which I don't know enough
about, but that can be
one way to try
Let's see, I think I saw something like this
recently
So, replacement for history
Yeah, that's why people use this history
package, I think that's
Oh yeah, that's it
New API for
How do I search this?
Like, mdn
history, API
replacement
I don't remember the new name
What is the new
Can I ask chatGP?
Maybe it doesn't know
We can ask
What's the name of the spec
that
supersedes
history API
for browsers
I've definitely read about
Yeah
There is, yeah, the new transition is going to
assume a navigation is happening
and it's going to slide in a new page
which is actually not what we're trying to do
viewTransitions
No, I think viewTransitions
has something to do with
I think that's different
It's about
making it look
nicer, right?
It's about navigating
It's meant to be different
than doing a manual push
state and changing parts of the page
where you can say start viewTransition
get a snapshot of what's on the page right now
and then replace the DOM here
It assumes DOM's being replaced
Yes, I found it
The new thing is called navigation API
It's window.navigation
Let's see if that's
Is that different?
Yeah
So maybe window.navigation
Let's see if I can
navigation API
blah blah blah
navigate
How do you
replace?
I actually don't see that
navigate
So if I go to navigate
options
the current state
info
history, replace
Okay, you can do that
Where is that?
I'm looking
through, oh yeah, it's addEventList or
navigate, this could work
So what you would do instead of history
is
inside of search
just search
It should be window.navigation
Oh, I'm actually not getting
the API
Is it too new?
I'm just going to try and navigate
Yeah, it's too new, it's experimental
Yeah, that's fine
So yeah, we navigate to that
and then options you can say
not replace
true, it's
history, replace
Okay
That'll do it
And let's try to
listen to, what is the
event handler on?
Just navigate
And it's also suggesting
an event.intercept
I don't know why
I don't know what that is, let's for now
ignore whatever that is
Yeah, that's intercepting
Yeah, I don't know
because you're already intercepting if you're listening
I guess
So I'm going to change this to
handleNavigate
and let's see if that
even gets triggered
Can you check?
Let's check
All right
Reload here
And as we type, it's actually not
It's not letting me type
Let me see here
It's not letting me
type
It's not letting me type
Uh
I just
I wonder if it's
re-fetching the page when I type
it's losing the context and then it's all
gone
Maybe we need to disable
some things that are happening, just to be sure
Yeah
Yeah, just don't do this part
but log it
Yeah, okay, let's do this
Oh, now I get
actual errors
Navigate is not defined. What?
Okay, okay
This is all, like, we're going down
the rabbit hole. Let's do it completely differently
I'm just going to
This is too much
We're going to do this
I wanted to know about the browser APIs, though
It's a shame
The browser API
We're going to invent our own browser APIs
I was thinking some custom events or something
We can do this
Yeah, we're just going to be
window on
URL changed
That's going to be our custom
I mean, this doesn't make any sense
but I don't want to
I think my patience
is a bit
Yeah, we're just going to have
Yeah, that'll do. Let's do that
That's, you know
callbacks
Yeah, I was going to do it a little bit more politely
This is fine
Yeah, we're just going to do this
and then we're going to
we're just going to do, like, callbacks
push
navigate
and then this is going to be
something like
callbacks
Yeah, just pop it off
or slice
Oh
Yeah, that worked
Maybe like this
Can we see if that
is called?
Let's see
Handled
Yeah
Okay, so now let's try to update
the state as well
Oh, it's filtering
Is it working?
Oh my god!
Okay, it hides the search box
while we're searching because we put it
behind the wrong suspense
but oh my god, it works
So, wait, this is actually the part
that we can fix
So the issue is that
Can you demonstrate the problem?
Yeah
Yeah, I can follow you
Perfect
Can you show the
I guess I don't see it because the stream is not fast enough
I don't know if people see it
The problem is
Let's increase the delay so that
it's, yeah, okay
So the search bar disappears
because we actually need to get
the server component output
And the server component output is waiting
for that filter
or whatever
to fetch the data before
we can even know what to show
and so it suspends
And so the way
the way you handle it
One thing we could do
is maybe restructure it a little bit
so that the
search input isn't kind of blocked
on anything
But the
idiomatic solution in React is
router changes
Again, this is
primarily if you're developing the framework
I think this is something like
if you're making a framework for
server components, this is something
you should probably know, is that
the route changes
so the set states
that lead the route changes
should be wrapped into transitions
So what I'm going to do is
I'm going to import startTransition
from React here
Ooh, yes
I wanted a transition demo
Okay
And so I'm going to wrap the set state
into a transition
And so this tells React that
actually it's okay for
the screen to be inconsistent
So even though we know we're fetching something
we're waiting for something to happen
it's okay to let that
We don't need to immediately
show the spinner, we can actually wait
for that thing to be
complete enough that
Oh!
I've been wanting to understand transition for so
long and I get it
I see the use case there
And everything works
Yeah, and so what should also
work now is
Cached ones are faster
Yeah, so now if you type the same thing again because you've
cached the server component
the response is
Ooh, yeah
Oh, this is mind-blowing
I love that cache was involved too
The other thing we can try
which I don't know if it's going to work
because we had a bug related to this
but I think maybe it works
is I'm going to go to search.jsx
and I'm also going
to
Yeah, so
Okay, yeah
Okay
I'm also going to
add useTransition here
So if you only want to start a transition
you can just start a transition
But if you want to show visual feedback in the
component tree itself
when something is being refetched
and you don't want it to be just
like the user doesn't know what's happening
you can
have useTransition here
And that gives you this
Let's call it startTransition
useTransition
So that gives you this expanding Boolean
And so what you can do is
I know that
You know, this is
I'm actually going to
I'm going to rename this
I'll call this
Well, okay, that's what I'm going to do
I'm going to call this window.router.navigate
to here
And I'll just
That's supposed to be
your framework
I mean, you wouldn't put it on the window variable, of course
But it would be like
Yeah, but that's
We're going to go back to the root.client
And I'll just
This is going to be our toy router that has
navigate the URL
And so this is the part that actually does
the
This is the URL
It does the state and then
It calls
the callbacks we registered
So I
think
window.router.navigate
replace state URL
Okay
Yeah, and so this is
Say again
We're hitting a client error
What is the error?
The user, no, no, not that
Callbacks is not defined. Okay
It's just a
Yeah, it's just a typo
I think I deleted it accidentally
Yeah, we just deleted it
Okay, let's try again
Okay, that's working
Yeah, so now let's go back to the search
And let's say
Oh, and look at this
We can actually see all the requests coming down the wire too
It's going to
keep doing this
So let's add a little bit
Yeah, that's a new
Can I add this back?
This is going to look a little bit ugly
But I'm just going to add like a
Also like if is pending
Then I'm going to
add like a little
You know, like a little
I don't know
Margin left
Two or something
I don't remember how to do it
Sure
But let's see
Yeah
Yeah, I think italics are what we want here
That should work
So can we see
if that does anything?
It looks like it is
Yeah, we get a little
We get a little loading
flash
But if we do something
and it's cached
It's pretty much instant
It shows a little flash of it
while it fetches from the cache
Yeah
So the way you deal with like
So what we kind of want to do here
is like we want to show
You see like
this you are looking for
So this is the
example that we have
It doesn't quite make sense
Well
So this is the thing that will be updated later
Because like we need to go to the server
And like that part is like on the server
And we could have moved that to the client
And like show it in the search box instead
So I think it just depends on like
What kind of UI do you want?
Like do you want
You know
Like other patterns could be
Like grayed out
While the
While you're refetching it
So that's another
kind of common pattern
Yeah
Maybe do you want to
try to do that?
Sure, yeah
Could be fun
It's a little bit
It's a little bit trickier
to figure out how to do this
Yeah, okay, I'll be honest
I was reading something from chat and missed the last 20 seconds
of what you said. Can you say that again?
Yeah, I was saying
Now like we
We can kind of
I don't know
Maybe we should go through the code
And just kind of recap
Because like we have a solution now
So it seems like a good time
Like we built a tiny framework
That does a little bit of routing
In a way that
Works with server components
So maybe it's a good time to recap
What's going on in our
setup. Do you want to try to do that?
Let's do it
Yeah, so I
Will try to trace it from the top
But basically what we built
Is a
Search box
That's able to have just a little bit
Of client-side JavaScript in order to
Store a state
Of what you're trying to search for
And then anytime you put in an input
We're updating the URL bar up here
At the top
And anytime that you update the URL
We want to re-render
The parts of the page that depends on that URL
Here the part that depends is
The amount of albums that we're showing
So when we say search post, we want to
Go to the server, figure out which albums
Actually have the word post in them
And then send that new result
Down to the client
Without actually having to render all of those albums
With client-side JavaScript
So if we head over to our root
Client where we're doing this
Slight hack, but you could formalize
This into a framework as Dan mentioned
In here
The client is able to trigger
Navigate, or any client component
Is able to trigger a navigate command
Which will tell it the URL
It wants to go to, we're going to use
The web standard history API to update
That state, and then pass in
A callback here that's going
To trigger
Actual navigation events
So we mentioned it a little bit earlier
But we had a, now I'm actually
Losing where it is, but yeah
Way down here is where we're actually going to
Fetch the server component and render it
Onto the page
But up here we're using an effect
To say anytime that you
Navigate on the page, first off we're going to
Start a transition, which
I'm still wrapping my head around a little bit
But it's basically saying, keep the DOM
That you already have
Until all the other async stuff has resolved
And then replace it
Once all of that is settled, is that kind of what it's doing?
It's, yeah, I would maybe
And again, just to clarify
This file we're looking at, that's not
That is the part that's the framework part
This is the framework part
It's not the part that you're
You don't need any effects here
As a server components user or something like this
So this is like the framework router part
Really
Actually I just realized that we made one
Omission, which is, I think we still need
To handle pop state
Because we want the back button to work, right?
So we want the back button to also
Update the
So I think that should
That should give us the
Well, I guess we don't, we replaced
State, so it's, you're not going to see it
Yeah, you're not going to see it
But yeah, this is another thing
That frameworks deal with, where if you
Don't want to have like a full page refresh
Every time, because if you did this fully server
Side, we could anytime
You type in the input, send a form request
Refresh the page
And send that new stuff down
But here we want to say, don't refresh the whole page
Keep it where it is, we're going to
Handle those changes to the URL
Bar ourselves, and we're going to
Make sure like, when you do all your web standard
Back buttons, they still work
And when you actually navigate
We don't want to blow away the app
And re-render it top to bottom, we want to keep it where it is
And trigger anyone that
Cares about the transition to also
Show little loading states
Yeah, so just to clarify
The start transition stuff here
It doesn't prevent
It doesn't have anything to do with
Reloading the page completely
Because React wouldn't reload the page
We're just set in state
There's no reason to reload the page
What happens here
Is it just prevents
React from hiding content
That was already visible
Like if you're interacting with
A search input, you don't want that
Input to get hidden, because
We're waiting
Our new state is this response
From the server that's still streaming in
So start transition just says
This state update is not urgent
You don't have to
React doesn't have to
React can wait
Until we have something
Meaningful to show
So in reality what that means
Is it wouldn't wait
It will wait long enough
Not so that
It doesn't have to hide any existing content
But for example
If your server response
Includes some new suspense boundary
With a bunch of stuff inside
It's not going to wait for that
Because there's no reason to
But start transition
Is this opt-in
This is not urgent
So you don't have to hide a bunch of stuff
While we're waiting
Keep things as they are
And then we can keep track of them
Inline in the search component
It has an inline indicator
That it's parent
Is actually refetching
But yeah
This is kind of what it is
That's what happens inside the framework
But if we forget this file exists
And we just approach it from
I think it's helpful to describe it
From the server components
Point of view
As a user you don't even have this root client.js file
It's somewhere in the framework
But as a user where do you start
Where does the story start
For a user
Gotcha
Because that's the boundary that we set
With suspense
Anytime you
Well we can't see it anymore
But it used to
It'll sort of show that fallback
And then show the whole result
But what we've done is we've put the search box
Alongside the stuff that's loading
So in order to make sure all of
The stuff you're looking at in the search box itself
Aren't as you mentioned
Removed from the page
Or changed in some way
Transition is the way to do that
And I'm assuming
Use transition is a pretty global thing
So when you start transition
Is it based on parents
Where if a parent starts a transition
The child picks it up here
No
It's really about the state updates
It's like whatever you
Whichever set state calls happen
Inside of a strategic goal
They are kind of marked as
This stuff is not urgent
And react will display the output
When the stuff is ready
But what I meant more
I think if we ignore all this wiring
And we focus on how you approach it as a user
The entry point
Is really root.server.js
That's where the story starts
From the user perspective
And so you kind of just see it as
You have a root component
Like in this case server root
That accepts the search
And it doesn't matter if it's the first time it loads
Or if it's like a refresh
The way you think about it is the same
It's like you got a response
You got a request
You're going to re-render the tree
And so you think about it as
I received some search query
I'm going to pass it to albums
Albums passes it to
This searchable album list
Which also runs on the server
This is where we
Actually do the filtering
And then we render the search box
And the list of albums
And so the search box
Is kind of
This is where
This is where this other side
Of the flow triggers
Where it's like when I tap into the search
I want to navigate
As a user
I just want to navigate here
And then that's
The whole story
Because now it's the server
Like we're again in the server
In root.server.js
And we just kind of render again
Using the new search value
So you don't really
Think of it as state management
Right
In fact we could even
Just for fun we could even delete
The state here
I believe we could get rid of the
State completely
And this could just be uncontrolled input
That has default value
Equals initial search
And it has this onChangeHandler
That just does the navigation
Doesn't do anything else
And I think it should still work
It actually does
Yeah so there's like no state management
Here
There's no managing caches yourself
Or you just want to change some data
You just
Re-render the page
But then it doesn't recreate the DOM
It doesn't recreate the DOM
Yeah
And the boundary that was like
If you don't have a transition
It will use the suspense fallback
So one thing I'm wondering
Inside of root server
If we remove the suspense wrapper
What will happen?
Do we need transition anymore?
Let's try
I don't know
I think maybe it would
Work without a transition
I think
But it's
Well
I guess it depends on where you want
To remove the transition
They're nested
Just to be able to show the
IsPending
Because the routers should always
Navigate in transitions
But we can also wrap it in extra time
To get this
Is it happening
For feedback
Yeah
And so how does it know when
IsPending is done?
Is that when everything down the parent
Chain of components is now rendered?
Not quite
It's
I think conceptually
The way it's implemented
There are different ways to do it
But I think conceptually you can imagine it
As
It kind of spawns
A new parallel universe
Where the state is
If we go to
root.client.js
And you see that
It does this set URL
Call
Traditionally this would mean
The state changed
Get the new thing on the screen
Immediately
If we get rid of startTransition
In both places
We would see traditional re-rendering
Behavior where
It's kind of
We changed this, now it has to update
To reflect what's in the state
We don't have the
JSX tree for what's in the state
That's why it's showing
The closest suspense spinner
Which
You would need to add
And the analogy that I like to use
For this is git
So if you work on main
If you only work on main
And then
You
Make a change that
You start refactoring something
And you change
One file
And
It's not done until you finish refactoring
Your project is kind of
In the loading state
It's not ready
And the users would see
Imagine you refactored in production
Your users would see
That you're doing it
And that's why we don't do it this way
We start a branch, we work in a branch
And then we think
This is enough to ship
To the main branch
And so transitions are kind of the same concept
It's like branches
It's like you're telling React
Here's a set state I want you to do
But actually start
Working on it
In background
Start preparing it
You can almost imagine
You had two screens
And one screen was what the user sees
And the other screen
Is background stuff
And on the screen
With the background stuff
You would see a big loading indicator
Because nothing is ready yet
And then it would kind of gradually refine
To get
With the server data
And at some point you have enough server data
That you don't
You wouldn't need to hide anything to show it
You wouldn't need to hide any
Existing content
So this is where React commits the transition
So React is like
We have enough of the tree
That we wouldn't need to hide anything
Nothing would
Disappear under you
It's automatic
You don't think about this as a user
But that's the heuristic we use
We're going to show you
The output as soon as we have enough
That
It doesn't feel disruptive
Because nothing disappears
From under you
Right
So React commits transitions off
To decide what if I delete it here
What if I remove it here
What if we remove the suspense boundary
And I think it will still take some time
To really feel it out
Because I'm sure you use it
In a lot of different contexts
But for the search box it makes sense to me
Where you definitely want to start transition here
Because we want
To be able to track
Like okay this
We've started something
We don't know when it's done
All we want to do is show that it is pending
And then as soon as React
Has figured out
Everything
It's resolved all the components down the tree
I'm trying to find the perfect vocabulary here
And I don't think I have it yet
I wouldn't say
It doesn't need to resolve everything
Because maybe you have some new components
And there's no reason to wait for them
So as soon as you have enough
That would be not embarrassing
To show
That's kind of how I explain it
As soon as you have a decent
Floating state
And it's determined automatically
So you don't need to think about it
Yeah
It's contextual
We know you called this from the search box
So we know what this search box
Depends on
The parents that it has in order to render that search box again
No
That's not how it works
It's not conceptual
I think that's kind of the cool thing
About this
It really doesn't care
Because you could be navigating to another page
You could be navigating
From a feed page
To a profile page
And then let's say on the profile page
You have profile cover
And then you have
Profile timeline inside of suspense
So what that means
And then
My start transition is built into the router
So it's not
Just for this search box
Like here
We could completely remove start transition
Like we just want to show a state
Tracking what's going on
Yeah so here it's not essential
Because we only added it here
To get this access to this is pending
Where it's important
Is only at the router level
And so what this does
What this does
Here for example
If we're moving from feed to profile
And then profile has like a cover
And a timeline
Wrapped in suspense
What's going to happen is that
If profile cover needs to load some data
For example profile name
And your avatar
Then the router will wait
For that to be ready
It won't teleport you to this empty profile page
That doesn't have anything
Because we don't have a decent loading state
For it
We don't have something to show yet
But then as soon as
The profile cover is ready
And the remaining stuff is wrapped in suspense
It will be like
Now I can actually move to this page
Because I can show the cover
And then the rest will have a spinner
So this is what it does
It just opts you into this
It doesn't have to happen right away
But we're going to wait enough
Until we have something decent to show
And it's based on this heuristic
So it doesn't really care
From which component
Because like you see here
It's really at the root level
So it doesn't even know
You're calling it from search input
It doesn't care where you're calling it from
Yeah
I guess in the other example I was trying to figure out
When is pending resolved
And it sounds like there's more heuristics involved
Than just like
Everything down the tree has re-rendered
There's a lot more to it
Well it's not a lot more
It's a very simple heuristic
But it's very non-intuitive
Because we only figured it out
In the initial design
It didn't work like this
And this is the most natural
It's a bit weird
Because understanding the heuristic
Is pretty difficult
But then the way it works is very natural
So you don't have to think about it
You don't need to know about it as a user
If you're curious
As a framework author
How it works
Then it's really
Can we
Every time
We're about to
We got some new data
We could maybe make some progress
On rendering the tree
And then every time
We're like okay
For now it seems like we're done
We've done everything we could
And we make a decision
Is this enough to
Show this to the user now
Or do we have to keep waiting longer
And the way we make the
Decision is pretty simple
It's if we
Have rendered it now
Would we have to hide any
Existing content
So this moment
Where the search bar disappeared
Because something there was not ready
And there was a suspense boundary above
It kind of means we're
Resuspending it
It wasn't here
But it has to disappear
Because some part of the tree is not ready
And so if we have to do this
We're not going to commit it
No, let's keep waiting a bit longer
But
If we have enough of the tree
That we don't need to hide any
Existing content
It's just maybe we have some new content
That's not fully fetched yet
We would be like, yeah, sure, let's go ahead
Let's show it
I think I'm getting it then
It's definitely based on what you have now
And what you're trying to get
And if
You have enough of a match
In what you're trying to get that you're not going to hide anything
Then we'll go ahead and resolve it
Exactly
That's how it works
It's a very simple thing
But it's hard to wrap your mind around it
But I find it
Kind of fascinating
Because it is a solution
To the
If you ever developed a router
In traditional kind of JavaScript
Ecosystem
There were always
You always had to make
This tradeoff between
How do I know
When to show the route
During navigation
And different routers solve this
Differently
So
In some routers
I think maybe Ember router
I'm not sure
But in some routers
They wait for all data
For the new route to be ready
And then they transition you
To the new route
And so the benefit of this is that the user
Doesn't see this immediate
Big spinner
That's like, you're pressing a link
And you have nothing to show yet
And you have to wait for everything to load
Which could be slow
So ideally
You wouldn't have to
And then the other extreme
Which I think most React solutions
At least for some time
It depends on how we configure it
But at least it was very common
That routing happens immediately
So you press a link
You immediately re-render
Like you rendered a new page
But maybe it's not ready
And so I think the beautiful thing
About this paradigm
Is that it lets you draw
The boundary exactly where you want
Just by placing suspense
Around it
Because the router
Uses transitions by default
So you don't have to
By default everything is sticky
So until everything is ready
It doesn't do it
But then suspense lets you say
No, actually this part of the tree
That's okay to wait a little bit
It doesn't have to wait for it
So it's kind of like inverse await
Where you say
This part, it's independent
I wrap it in a loading state
Now transitions won't wait for it anymore
And I think that's maybe
A natural way to explain it
It's like by default
Everything is sticky
And suspense is what unsticks it
Yeah
That's a wild way to think about it
Because there wasn't really
A convention for this before
You were just going to grab whatever the tree is
And plop it on the page
You can't use heuristics to know
What was there before in the new thing
It's not really like diffing
But it is figuring out
You don't really want to suspend again
We don't want to keep suspending every time we type in the search box
We've suspended before
And we don't want the user to see it
So if we do a start transition
We can still get the new state
Or the new text inside the search box
But we're going to avoid
Blowing it away while we're doing it
Yep
Very cool
Okay, I'll also admit that I'm like
I'm running on fumes
I had breakfast like eight hours ago
At this point
I didn't think we would go this long
I definitely thought we were going to go for like two hours
Maybe two hours thirty
You've been super generous with your time
But I'm going to push this up
To make a separate branch
Just in case people want to see
Co-authored by Danny Ramone
Absolutely
We'll call it, oh boy, Router Toy
It's what I kind of liked
RSC Demo also
RSC Stream Demo
If anyone's wondering what the Twitch Stream Demo had
Yeah, we'll do that
And if anyone wants to play with this
I'm tired from just following along
Man, thanks for sticking through here
In the chat, thank you
But I shared it just above
If anyone wants to play with this
Toy implementation of React Server
Components, we never actually got to look
At a framework, we built our own
But this is simple RSC
It doesn't even have a readme at the moment
I was very undergun trying to get it in
For the stream today
So I'll try to add some docs
And maybe explain the dev panel a little bit more
But the goal is to not add
Any more features to this
Maybe delete the files that we don't use
So that, like, I think you have
A bunch of files that we didn't end up using
Yeah, I think the Bjork album's gone
The like button was never pulled in
Counter was never pulled in
That should be it
And I'll double check on this
In case it was floating around somewhere
Yeah, it still is
Maybe let's rename root.server.js
To something like
Server root, and then
The root.client.js to something like
Router, or I don't know
Ideally we would
Maybe make a
I'd like to see some separation so that it's clear
This is the framework part, this is not the part
You're supposed to be writing
No, exactly
Yeah, I definitely prefer to
Oh, did we actually get an index file?
Where did this come from?
I think this is just like an old thing
Yeah, this is not being used
I wanted to call it
We decided on index and bootstrapping
As like loose names
I don't mind it
But index feels right for that
Because that's like the index route
And this is just
Yeah, there's a few ways to put this one
Maybe not the index
Maybe like page
Or something
Oh, page is good
Next.js style
This can be
Route handler
Well, it does a lot of things
It mounts it onto the page
Yeah
Client
I think
Can we move it
Out of the source directory
And put it
Closer to the handler
I think conceptually
It's related to this handler.js
In a way
It's like the client part of it
I hear what you're saying
Or maybe you could move to source
Like make a directory called framework
And then there would be
Like server.js
And client.js
Yeah
Router.server.js
I don't know
I went back and forth so long
I landed on the remix names
And I still don't like them
So
I just think it's important to
Make sure that people don't think that this is the stuff
You're supposed to be writing
The actual application code is just
Page.js
Search.js and searchablealbum.js
Yeah
We could call it
Underscore internals
Yeah
Bubble it up
The only thing left to do is to
Track down a couple hard-coded things
I think I was pretty
I wasn't great about this
So that would be page now
I'm hoping
Also this is not the client part anymore
Yeah
Wherever we did root.client
We did that
Okay
Yeah
Oh so let's rename search to
Searchbox because that's how you named it
Oh yeah I noticed
We were a little inconsistent
Okay I renamed it
Okay
And I'll move
The filter albums function down
So that it doesn't obscure the
Component
Build successfully
I think everything works
What?
Awesome
That's searchbox
That's that
This index file is just not a thing
I don't know why it keeps coming back actually
Why does it keep coming back
Nice
Maybe stick it in support
I hear you
I don't know about that
I don't know
Yeah I think internals is still
Where I'm sitting
I've also seen engine as a convention
But that's a little more
We can also call it
Yeah
That's fine
It does kind of indicate you can have
Multiple routes but
It is a router
It's like toy router
Toy router
Yeah I mean the whole thing's
A toy so I'm not going to call it that
Yeah that's good
Yeah that'll
Work fine
Okay
I'm feeling good about these names
And the only squiggles we have should just be
Yeah we're abusing window
And async
Is not part of like the
Built in TypeScript JSX thing
It's kind of funny that JSX has been hijacked
As like this standard that can be highlighted
The same way for everyone
Because you can use it different ways
And you end up with funky situations like this
Where some people support promises
And some people don't
But it's still JSX
Yeah
Why does it keep showing client part
I think I deleted this comment before
Yeah
Sometimes LiveShare
Gets out of sync
And luckily we've been pretty in sync this whole time
Perfactor
New naming
All right
That's up
Beautiful
Yeah
Well I'll go back to our big faces I think
Your lighting's gone down a bit
I have some more time
But yeah let me
Make sure of the branch
Before we sign off
Okay my computer's chugging
Y'all can find the branch don't worry about it
But hey if you enjoyed the stream
I try to do Twitch streams
Every week
Thursdays at
What is it now
It should be 3pm eastern
But we bumped it forward a little bit
For this special edition stream
But I've been doing React server components a lot
I've been going really deep on it
Because I'm also someone who works on Astro
Which is a meta framework
It would be cool to support some implementation
Of server components if not for the migration story
So I'm going to be playing with it a lot more
And yeah
Drop a follow if that interests you
You can also of course follow Dan
If you're not I don't know why
But he's around Twitter
Dan underscore Abramov
You can see the title of this stream
I think that is the Twitter handle
Is there anyone else
That you want people to find you
Or any closing thoughts
I don't think I want people to find me
All right
Enough of them have found me
I just want to say I really appreciate you
Offering
For me to be on this stream
And also
You really did the homework
I mean the only reason
We were even able to
Build a mini framework
Is because you've already built 80% of it
So I really appreciate
Doing the homework
So well
It's really impressive
And there aren't
There isn't that much documentation around it
But yeah
Thank you so much for
Creating this opportunity
It was really fun
Yeah
I mean thanks for just saying yes
On a random Twitter DM
I wasn't sure
But I thought like
Because I saw the stream you did with
Ken C Dodds and others
And it was like this stream was great
And I was like
Can we actually
Draw a flow diagram
And see some code
Because conceptually
There's a lot going on
So yeah
I think this went over really well
And the replay will be on YouTube also
I'll share the link in the chat again
But I'll try to upload this live stream over there
It might go up by tomorrow
Because downloading four hours of stream from Twitch
And uploading four hours of stream to YouTube
It might be a little bit
To see if we can get like
The let's build a router part
Separate from the let's understand server components
Because one's more intermediate and advanced
Than the other
But yeah
Okay
Yeah well good having you
Thanks for stopping in
And oh
Let's actually find someone to raid
Before I hop off
Does anyone have suggestions
What does it mean
What is raiding
I don't understand
It's something you can do on Twitch
To take your audience and push them
Into another stream that's active
Oh
Are they like forced
To do that
Well I mean you can just stop watching
If you don't want to do that
It's kind of like YouTube autoplay
Yeah
But it hosts inside of yours
And you can leave
It's I don't know it's a fun system
But I'll raid Cassidy
Because she's great and does a ton of React tutorials
And everything
We still had a ton of people sticking around
Thank y'all so much
Drop a follow for the next stream
Obviously do all of that
But yeah
See y'all around
Bye
Okay